<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of the covenant of redemption Wherein is laid the foundation of all our hopes and happiness. Briefly opened and improved. By Samuel Willard, teacher of a church in Boston. [Three lines from Psalms]</title>
            <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2274A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W38208</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897886</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170983</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96532)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170983)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2538:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of the covenant of redemption Wherein is laid the foundation of all our hopes and happiness. Briefly opened and improved. By Samuel Willard, teacher of a church in Boston. [Three lines from Psalms]</title>
                  <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 165, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Benj. Harris over against the [Old-Meet]ing-House,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Increase Mather.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks errata and all after page 158, and title page is damaged, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Covenant theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:4"/> THE Doctrine OF THE COVENANT OF REDEMPTION.</p>
            <p>Wherein is laid the Foundation of all our HOPES and HAPPINESS.</p>
            <p>Briefly Opened and Improved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Willard,</hi> Teacher of a Church in <hi>BOSTON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 89. 3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have made a Covenant with my Choſen, I have Sworn to</hi> David <hi>my Servant.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Boſton,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benj. Harris</hi> over-again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>5word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-Houſe.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>92.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170983:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THE Great and Glorious God who has an abſolute Dominion over his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, might (had he pleaſed) have dealt with. Men in a way of Soveraignty only, requiring Duty and Obedience from them, without any promiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But he has ſeen Good to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſact with them in a Covenant way. There are but Two Covenants eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally differeing which the Moſt High has made with men, <hi>Viz.</hi> That of <hi>Works,</hi> And that of <hi>Grace.</hi> The first Covenant which man whilst in Paradiſe, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in, is rightly termed a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works,</hi> becauſe <hi>Works or Doing,</hi> was the Condition of it. Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſoon broken, and ſo made Null, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then the Lord out of his Infinite Goodneſs, was pleaſed to eſtabliſh another Covenant The firſt was made with a Righteous P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, and ſo a <hi>Covenant of Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:7"/> between the Holy God and him. This latter was made with ſinners and is therefore a <hi>Covenant of Reconciliation.</hi> And it is ſitly stiled the <hi>Covenant of Grace:</hi> Not but that there was Grace in the Firſt Covenant, for His Divine Majeſty did infinitely condeſcend in binding himſelf to his Creature: but to do thus to a fallen, forlorn ſinful Creature, is <hi>by way of Eminent Grace.</hi> The Scripture ſpeaketh expreſly of <hi>Two Covenants, Gal</hi> 4. 24. And that not only as <hi>Diverſe,</hi> but as <hi>Oppoſite</hi> and differeing in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The Law of Faith is ſet in direct oppoſition to the Law of Works. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 27. <hi>For a man to find the Life of his hands,</hi> to live by his own Righteouſneſs; and for him to depend ſolely upon the Righteouſneſs of another, that is, of Jeſus Christ for Life and Salvation, are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things. And from thence it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a man to be under both the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants at the ſame time; he cannot be the Child of two Mothers, the Child of <hi>Hagar,</hi> and of <hi>Sarah</hi> too.</p>
            <p>That the Covenant of Grace has for
<pb facs="tcp:170983:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſubstance of it been the ſame in all Ages, differing only in Circumſtances &amp; as to the manner of diſpenſations is denied by the <hi>Old Pelagians,</hi> and by <hi>Socinians, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians,</hi> and ſome <hi>Baptiſts</hi> at this day. But the Scripture aſsureth us, <hi>That Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers under the Old-Teſtament were not made perfect without us. Heb.</hi> 11. 40. They &amp; we are ſaved by the ſame Chriſt &amp; by the ſame Covenant, the Mediator of the Covenant has always been the ſame, <hi>Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to day, &amp; for ever the ſame. The Son of God was an Interceſſor for his People before his Incarnation.</hi> Zach. 1: 12. <hi>Believers under the Old-Teſtament</hi> were <hi>ſecured by him.</hi> Neither is there ſalvation in any other. <hi>If then the Partriarchs were ſaved (as we know they were) it was by Jeſus Chriſt: No man was ever ſaved ſince the world began but by him. Under the Old-Teſtament Faith in Chriſt was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in order to Juſtification &amp; Salvation</hi> To him give all the Prophets Witneſs that through his Name, whoever believeth in him ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins. <hi>Promiſes which do concern Spiritual and Eternal</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>as well as Temporal bleſſings, were made to Old-Teſtament believers.</hi> Our Saviour proveth that the bodys of Saints ſhall have a Glorious Reſurrection to Eternal Life from the Covenant made with Abraham. <hi>They of old, Looked for a City which has Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, whoſe maker and builder is God.</hi> Which, if Heaven (and not Temporal Bleſſings only) had not been Promiſed them, they would not have done. Now if there is an Identity as to the Mediator, the Condition, the promiſes of the Covenant made with Believers in the days of the Old Teſtament and of the New, the Covenant muſt needs be effectually the ſame. When therefore by the <hi>Old &amp;</hi> the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> that of Works and of Grace are intended, the diſtribution is of the <hi>Genus</hi> into its <hi>Species.</hi> But when the Covenant of Grace as under the Legal or Evangelical diſpenſation, is meant (&amp; ſo it often is in the Scripture) the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction is of the ſame ſubject according to its various adjuncts.</p>
            <p>There is another Covenant which that of Grace is built upon, Viz. <hi>The Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> That there have been bleſſed Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions between God the Father and the Son from the Days of Eternity, concerning the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Elect, is a glorious Truth, which (not the light of nature but only) the written word of God has revealed; That ſpeaketh of <hi>Gods Purpoſe</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:9"/> 
               <hi>and Grace given us in Chriſt Jeſus before the world began,</hi> and of <hi>Eternal Life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed before the world began.</hi> Theſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſactions were Foederal. The father ſaid of the Son <hi>[im Taſim, ſi poſuerit] If he ſhall make his Soul an offering for Sin,</hi> Iſa. 53. 10. Whatever is required to a compleat formal Covenant between two diſtinct Perſons is to be affirmed, concerning what has paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Chriſt with reſpect unto the Redemption of thoſe that were from Eternity gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him; Articles of Agreement (to ſpeak after our Nature) have been concluded, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and exactly kept unto by them both. On this account the Lord Chriſt is ſaid to be a <hi>Surety.</hi> He is not only <hi>Fidejuſſor</hi> but <hi>Expromiſſor.</hi> He has ſo undertaken to anſwer for his Elect, as that they were many of them ſet at liberty before the price of their Redemption was actually payed &amp; that by vertue of this Covenant, wherein the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did take the word of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, that the thing ſhould in due time be performed. As to the Efficacy of his Death, <hi>He was ſlain from the Foundation of the World.</hi> Believers that dyed in the beginning of time went to heaven becauſe the Son of God had promiſed to lay down his life to ſatisfy divine juſtice in their behalf. Concerning the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> this Author has Publiſhed a judicious Treatiſe ten years ſince, whereby the Churches have been edified. He has here,
<pb facs="tcp:170983:9"/> with the like ſolidity diſcourſed on the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> ſhewing himſelf a workman that needs not be aſhamed. The Reader will find therein Goſpel Myſteries, with <hi>Brevity</hi> and yet Perſpicuity (which is rare) explained, confirmed, applyed, ſo as that both Learned and Unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (God has made us Debtors unto both) may thereby be built up in their most Holy Faith; in ſome more diſputable Points, He expreſſeth his own Judgement without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on thoſe whom He differs from. It has been controverted amongſt very Learned men, whether it is conſistent with the Rectoral Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of that God who cannot look upon ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, to pardon ſin without ſatisfaction made to his injured juſtice. <hi>Grotius, Voſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Voetius, Turretin, Heidan,</hi> and of our own Divines, the great <hi>Owen</hi> and Mr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> have inclined to the Negative in the Queſtion mentioned. But others of great name and worth, (and in particular Dr. <hi>Twiſs</hi> concerning whom our Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> in his Life of Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> does truly affirms that he was if any of this age a Star of the first Magnitude) are for the Affirmative, with whom the Worthy Author does concur, but with ſuch Modesty and Cander as no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious perſon tho' of a differing Sentiment, can be offended at him. In Queſtions ſo Extrafun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, (as long as the beſt of us know but in
<pb facs="tcp:170983:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> part) we may (to uſe <hi>Auſtins</hi> expreſſion) be diverſly perſwaded <hi>Salva ſide et Caritate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the God of truth, bleſs theſe endeavours for glory to his own Name, the edification of his People, and the rejoicing of his Servant, and Grant that both Speaker and Hearers, Writer and Readers, may have Joy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Day of Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Boſton, New-England.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 6th. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Increaſe Mather</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170983:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CHAP I. An Introduction.</head>
            <p>THE Unparallel'd and Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible Love of God to Sinful Man, diſplayed in the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Affair of his <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation;</hi> is the great thing celebrated in the Scriptures; and is that which invites our moſt frequent, and raiſed Meditations. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore prays for his <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that they, together <hi>with all Saints, might be able to comprehend it, Eph.</hi> 3. 17, 18, 19. Nor is there one paſſage in this whole Tranſaction, but what is admirable and precious; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foundation of our hope to enjoy Eternal Life, who are by <hi>Nature Children of Wrath;</hi> and but for it, the whole forefeited Race of <hi>Adam</hi> muſt have periſhed hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170983:11"/> and everlaſtingly. The Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this is truly ſurprizing: Time is too ſhort; Eternity but long enough to ſpend in the Survey of it. This Love is a Fountain which ſprang up in, and runs down to Eternity. It never knew a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor ſhall ever come to an end.</p>
            <p>Now there are two general heads, unto which our Speculation of this Glorious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery may be reduced.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Proviſion which God made for our deliverance before time, in the days of Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The things which are done in time for the actual Accompliſhment of it. They that would Search the Love of God to the Original, and follow it up to the Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of it, muſt aſcend beyond the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the World, and look for it in that Eternity which had no Beginning. Not only the <hi>things</hi> that he hath done for us, but the <hi>thoughts</hi> alſo which he had of us, do Recommend his Tranſcendent Good Will unto us; the Meditation of them was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry choiſe to <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 139. 17. That God bare Love to his People <hi>of Old,</hi> He Himſelf aſſures them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 3. Theſe Thoughts of his had lain hid from us, but that he was pleaſed to Reveal them to us in his Word, from whence we muſt bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170983:11"/> our Information: and it is our Duty and will be our Advantage to enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, ſo far as we have Scripture Light to direct us. The former of theſe is that which is Deſigned in the Enſuing <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> by Divine Aſſiſtance. and in truth, all our Speculations about the latter will be dark, ſhort, and confuſed, except we trace them hither. We ſhall neither know where our Salvation began, nor what Security there is for it, or how to act our Faith aright about it. Here is the <hi>Idea</hi> or <hi>Exemplar</hi> of all that is done in bringing of Fallen Man to Glory: here is the Ratification or Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the whole concern: here we are acquainted with the leading Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to, and unfailing Aſſurances of the <hi>Vocation, Juſtification, and Glorification</hi> of all Gods Choſen Ones: for here we find the firſt Link of that Chain, and that which faſtens all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29, 30. The beſt and moſt ſuitable notion under which this great Affair may be repreſented to us for our Information, and ſatisfaction, is that of a <hi>Covenant;</hi> which being of ſo much uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, is the more eaſily underſtood: and becauſe it carries in it the ſtrongeſt confirmation of things that Humane Nature is capable of, muſt needs be moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the eſtabliſhing of our Faith.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170983:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nor is this a meer notion of mans In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, but that which hath clear and firm footing in the Word of God, as will in its due place appear. Now this Covenant, is by ſome Divines called the <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>Suretyſhip;</hi> by others, the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption;</hi> becauſe there was in it a full Suretyſhip given for, and a firm Compact made about the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a number of Mankind, in order to their Salvation.</p>
            <p>The enquiry into, and right ſtating of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this <hi>Covenant,</hi> is of excellent advantage for our better underſtanding of the whole tenour of the Scriptures; the avoidance of many pernicious Errors which the ignorance of it, hath given advantage to take rooting among ſuch as call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Christians;</hi> the true apprehenſion of the Terms of the Goſpel Covenant; and the comforting of the Hearts of Gods Children, againſt the many Temptations which aſſault them. I ſhall therefore, as God ſhall pleaſe to aſſiſt me, endeavour to purſue it in this method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To ſtate the right notion of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>To prove from the Word of God, that there is ſuch a Covenant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>To Explain it in thoſe ſeveral things wherein the ſpecial nature of it may be rightly concerned.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170983:12"/>
               <item> 4 <hi>To ſhew the neceſſity of it in order to Fallen Mans Salvation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>To ſhew the Influence which it hath into the Covenant of Grace which is made with us.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>To draw ſome practica Inferences from it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER 2. <hi>The right Notion of the Covenant of Redemption Stated,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere are two enquiries apt to be made about a matter of Diſcourſe, <hi>viz. Anſit,</hi> and <hi>Quidſit,</hi> whether the thing be, and what it is. If the thing it ſelf be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for granted to be, the former is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeded; but it it be Suſpected, it muſt be Cleared: and either of theſe ſeems to claim the Precedency: for, though words be to ſignify things, yet they are often Dark, Ambiguous Aequivial; and till we know what they Indigitate, how ſhall we determine whether the thing be? And yet on the other hand, till we are ſatisfied that the thing is, it is ſuperfluous to enquire into the nature of it, leſt our diſpute
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170983:13"/> ſhould prove to be about a non entity. To avoid both of theſe, I ſhall here only give ſome brief general account of the thing intended by the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> in order to the proof of the Aſſertion that there is ſuch a thing; leaving the full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of it till afterwards.</p>
            <p>Let it then be here obſerved. It is certain that the whole concern of Mans <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> had it conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and determination in Gods eternal Decree. It is a ſure rule, <hi>That whatſoever God doth in time, he purpoſed to do it before time:</hi> for he <hi>worketh all things according to the counſel of his will, Eph.</hi> 1. 11. God is a wiſe Agent; he muſt therefore know his own works; and this knowledge muſt be eternal, or elſe it could not be Divine, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 18. <hi>Known unto God are his works from the foundation of the world.</hi> He is a free Agent, and ſo he doth nothing but what he will do: And that will had no beginning, being <hi>Immutable, Job</hi> 23, 13. <hi>he is of one mind and who can turn him?</hi> Now although the <hi>Decree</hi> of God, be with reſpect to him Decreeing, but one ſimple and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided act; yet, in reference to the things Decreed, it is various, or hath many parts, in it: for which reaſon the ſcripture ſpeaks of many <hi>thoughts</hi> and many <hi>purpoſes</hi> of his.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170983:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Among theſe <hi>Decrees,</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> deſerve to be peculiarly remarked by us; becauſe they contein in them the Idea of that ſpecial government by which God leads all reaſonable creatures to an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate of happineſs or miſery. And among theſe, that of <hi>Election</hi> carries in it matter of ſingular and eminent comfort to all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, who by the knowledge of their Faith, come to be acquainted with their Intereſt in, and Title to it. In which <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> there was not only the deſignation of the end, unto which the Creature was appointed, but alſo the laying out of the whole way in which they were to be brought unto the Attainment of that end. The end to which men are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by <hi>Election,</hi> is <hi>Eternal Life.</hi> That which is the end of our Faith, is the Deſign of Gods <hi>Election,</hi> and that is our <hi>Salvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 9. Among the means, that which ſhines forth moſt illuſtriouſly, is mans deliverance from Sin and Wrath by the <hi>Obedience</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> who is the Eternal Son of God, and in fulneſs of Time was made man, in order to his Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us. This way of mans <hi>Redemption,</hi> had a room in Gods Eternal Purpoſe: Our <hi>Election</hi> therefore was <hi>in him,</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Creation, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 4. Not that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170983:14"/> Chriſt as Mediator was the Meritorious procuring Cauſe of our <hi>Election;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in and by him we were to be made partakers of all the benefits which were to be the Fruits of this Electing Love to us. Hence then the Son of God was appointed to do thoſe things for us, which were to procure all theſe benefits to be beſtowed on us; and for this reaſon is he ſaid to be <hi>Slain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> Rev. 13. 8. not that he was actually ſo, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Deſignation of it; and ſo the Apoſtle expounds it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20. <hi>who was verily Foreordained before the Foundation of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Article in the Decree, is in the Scripture repreſented unto us, under the notion of a <hi>Covenant</hi> between <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and <hi>God the Son;</hi> as will appear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, together with the reaſon why it is exhibited under ſuch a notion. So that by the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> under our conſideration, we are to underſtand, <hi>An E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Compact clearly made, and firmly Ratified, between</hi> God <hi>the Father, and God the Son, about the Redemption and Salvation of a number of the Children of Men;</hi> and this is a Covenant diſtinct from that which we call the <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi> which paſt between God and Man at the firſt in <hi>Adam;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170983:14"/> as alſo from the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> or that <hi>of Grace,</hi> which is Indented between God and Man, in Chriſt as the <hi>Mediator</hi> of it. This is the thing about which our Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is, and which may be laid open in the Sequel.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>Scripture Evidence that there is ſuch a Covenant of Redemption.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat the Word of God doth not in Terms mention ſuch a Covenant by ſuch a Title, muſt be acknowledged: but that it doth give us the account of a <hi>Covenant,</hi> which cannot be Interpreted of any other, yea which fully amounts to the thing, may ſafely be affirmed. We read, Pſal 89. 3. <hi>I have made a Covenant with my Choſen, I have Sworn to David my Servant.</hi> There are divers Texts in Scripture, eſpecially in the Old Teſtament, which have a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, partly to the <hi>Type,</hi> partly to the <hi>Antitype;</hi> or to the <hi>Antitype</hi> under the <hi>Type:</hi> This Pſalm is one of thoſe portions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which <hi>David</hi> is made a notable <hi>Type</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170983:15"/> of Chriſt: Him therefore it mainly aims at. The Covenant with him, is here made the foundation of all Conſolation to the People of God: Here then we have.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject Matter, <hi>viz. A Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The firmneſs of it; <hi>I have made;</hi> Hebr. <hi>Cut,</hi> alluding to that Cuſtome men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in <hi>Jer.</hi> 34. 18. which was a ſolemn ratification; and <hi>I have Sworn;</hi> noting the Immutability of it, according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 17, 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Parties in it; God on the one hand; <hi>I:</hi> God is the Speaker, Chriſt on the other hand, expreſſed in two words: <hi>My Choſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n:</hi> noting both his <hi>Excellency,</hi> and his <hi>Election; David my Servant;</hi> which muſt needs ultimately aim at Chriſt, as many Expreſſions in the Pſalm will unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably evince, eſpecially thoſe in <hi>verſe</hi> 19. 22, verſe 28, 29. 35, 36. Chriſt is therefore elſewhere called <hi>David,</hi> ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 34, 37. 24. and if we would know what Covenant this is, the Context clearly indicates it, to be that which concerns the <hi>Redemption</hi> and Salvation of the People of God: for it was that wherein he was made helpful to his People, <hi>verſe</hi> 19. wherein he was Anointed to his Offices of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diating Redeemer, <hi>verſe</hi> 19, 20. made Gods <hi>Firſt-born,</hi> verſe 27. and hath an abiding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170983:15"/> Seed, <hi>verſe</hi> 36. we alſo read, Zech. 6. 13. <hi>The Counſel of Peace ſhall be between them both;</hi> which clearly points to this Covenant under conſideration.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall eſſay a little more particularly to make the thing evident. I will not here inſiſt upon the opening of the nature of a Covenant in general, having done it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treatiſe; the ſum whereof is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is a mutual obligation between two parties.</hi> That which I have now to do, is to make it manifeſt, that there is ſuch a tranſaction between thoſe two glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which amounts to, or is ſuitably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by a <hi>Covenant;</hi> and that with reſpect to fallen mans <hi>Redemption.</hi> In order to the clearing up of which, let it be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>That God in diſcovering of his mind to us, is pleaſed to accommodate his language to our capacity, clothing divine truths with ſuch words, as may beſt ſuit our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. When therefore we ſay, there is ſuch a Covenant, it intends that there is that which is <hi>Analogous</hi> unto, and holds a full proportion with ſuch a thing; and is beſt accommodated to our underſtanding and faith by ſuch a reſemblance. For evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this, let us lay together theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and they will amoun to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170983:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. That God hath from all Eternity <hi>Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> a number of Mankind to Glory. The Scripture is ſo full and clear for this, that it would be ſuperfluous to inſiſt upon it. This is the beginning of all ſaving good which comes to any of the Children of Men. From hence it is that Salvation takes its riſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3, 4, 5. 1 Theſ. 1. 4. 5. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto is the application of grace in Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Vocation reſtrained, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 46. <hi>Ro.</hi> 11. 7. and what elſe can be deſigned in that <hi>Everlaſting Love</hi> that God bears to men, from whence their Converſion proceeds? <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 3. nor can all the Evaſions of men, elude the application of theſe, and many more Scriptures, to <hi>Eternal Election.</hi> If Redemption and Salvation belong to the Works of God, then there was a <hi>Decree</hi> that paſt concerning them, unleſs we will deny that God works in them as a Cauſe by Counſel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in this <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Election,</hi> God hath appointed for his Choſen, not only the end to which he will bring them, which is Glory; but alſo the means which are requiſite in order thereunto. For this reaſon it is called the <hi>Counſel of his Will, Eph.</hi> 1. 11. now <hi>Counſel</hi> hath a proper and next reference unto the means. <hi>Counſel</hi> according to our conception of the thing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170983:16"/> 
               <hi>is a deliberate enquiry after the most ſuitable way for the accompliſhing of a Deſign which one hath in his thoughts;</hi> and is aſcribed to God after the manner of men. Wiſe Agents will contrive their Buſineſs in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their ſetting about it. Gods Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes are diſplayed unto us under the conſideration of end and means. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines with himſelf, both what to do, and how to do it: and this properly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the Eternal <hi>Idea</hi> of his; and for this reaſon he aſſures his people that he <hi>knows what his own thoughts are,</hi> Jer. 29. 11. <hi>i. e.</hi> what methods he hath contrived for the management of their Affairs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Gods ultimate end in this Deſign, being the advancement of the glory of his Grace; hence by a wiſe and blameleſs Counſel, he ordered the permiſſion of man to fall into ſuch a State of Miſery, as to put him into an abſolute need of a <hi>Redeemer.</hi> That mans Fall came within the compaſs of the Decree, muſt needs be concluded, except we will aſſert ſome things to come to paſs againſt or beſide Gods Will; which is to deny his actual Supremacy over the whole Creation; or how is that <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 11. true? Man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had not Fallen, if he had not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to permit it; In which he acted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170983:17"/> his holy Soveraignty beyond the capacity of any Impeachment by the Creature. His ſpotleſs Holineſs ſo ordered it, that no Iniquity could be laid to his Charge on this account, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141. 17. That the glory of his <hi>Grace</hi> was the end of this, ſo far as his Elect were involved in it, herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, becauſe he took the occaſion from hence, for the Illuſtration of that precious Attribute, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 20. and but for it the whole concern of <hi>Goſpel Grace</hi> had been excluded; and that this Fall of Man put him into an abſolute need of a <hi>Redeemer</hi> is manifeſt, both from the rigour of the Law, exacting death of all its Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, without any abatement, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 17. the utter impotency of man, by the deadly influence of the <hi>Apoſtaſy,</hi> to do any thing towards his own delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being left by it <hi>without ſtrength, Rom.</hi> 5. 6. and the dreadfulneſs of the miſery which he was under the efficacy of, and muſt undergo, if there were no Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23. either he muſt periſh with an <hi>Everlaſting Deſtruction,</hi> or there muſt be a powerful <hi>Redemption</hi> laid in for him. This is the fearful condition in which this whole Race is involved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence, among the means, the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Son of God was ſet apart in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170983:17"/> 
               <hi>Decree,</hi> to be a <hi>Redeemer.</hi> The Son of God was not only an <hi>actual</hi> Redeemer in time, but a <hi>choſen</hi> Redeemer from Eternity, and for that reaſon is called Gods <hi>Choſen One, Pſal.</hi> 89. 3. and his <hi>Elect,</hi> Iſa. 42. 1. That the Son of God came within the compaſs of the <hi>Decree,</hi> and had his Name written there, as one who was to become a <hi>Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> for his People, is manifeſt by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Teſtimony, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 23. <hi>I was ſet up from Everlaſting.</hi> It is the Son who is the true Wiſdom, that is brought in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here: the word <hi>[Set up]</hi> denotes the conſtituting of one in ſome Office; and therefore a noun from it ſignifies a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</hi> It doth not deſign his natural Coeſſentiality with his Father, but his being ordained to ſome Employment; and what was that but this of a Redeemer? hence is he called <hi>A Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> Rev. 13. 8. which muſt be intended with reſpect to the <hi>Decree.</hi> Hence our Election is involved in his, Eph. 1. 3, 4. Chriſt was not ſent in haſte into the World: it was not a raſh and indeliberate Undertaking of his, but it was all Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Counſel of God, in every paſſage relating to it, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 23. 8. 4. 27, 28. when therefore he came in the Fleſh, he profeſſeth that it was <hi>to do his Fathers Will,</hi> Pſal. 40. 7.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170983:18"/> 5 The Decree of God is a firm, ſtable, Immutable Purpoſe of his. A very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could ſay, <hi>Nulla est Litura in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis Sapientum.</hi> The <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> under a proud opinion of their infallible Wiſdom, ſet a Stamp of Immutability upon all their Laws. But this is peculiar and proper to the Purpoſes of God. Gods Wiſdom is like himſelf, Infinite: he can never be wiſer than he was, then when he eſtabliſhed his Decree. He did it in Counſel, and his after thoughts can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mend his former. It was his Will that things ſhould be ſo, and he hath but <hi>one Will,</hi> which is not to be <hi>altered, Job</hi> 23. 13. Nor can he ever want for Power to put that in Execution, which he hath purpoſed; for he can do every manner of thing. The Records of Eternity ſhall ſtand unſhaken; what he hath ſaid ſhall certainly come to paſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. 27.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Son of God, who was thus conſtituted Redeemer in the Decree, is a Perſon in the God-head, infinitely free and uncompellable. Though the Doctrine of a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in the <hi>Unity</hi> of the Divine <hi>Eſſence,</hi> be a Myſtery beyond the capacity of our ſhort Underſtandings to fathom; yet in as much as theſe are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170983:18"/> exhibited to us under the notion of three <hi>Perſons,</hi> each one having a diſtinct <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence,</hi> (though all have but one and the ſame <hi>Eſſence)</hi> we muſt therefore allow to each of them all that is <hi>Eſſential</hi> to the God head: and thus we are to conceive of each of them to have a <hi>Divine Will;</hi> though it be one and the ſame in all. The Son of God, being God, is in this reſpect <hi>Coequal</hi> with the Father; for this reaſon he challenged this <hi>Equality</hi> as his due, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6. and God calls him <hi>his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> Zech. 13. 7. He is thereupon incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Compulſion. So that, upon an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ſuppoſition, that the Son had not complied with his Fathers Will in this matter, he could not have been Decreed to be a Redeemer; and from this very Argument the Apoſtle proves, that what Chriſt did upon this account was his own voluntary act, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 5, 6, 7. The Father no ſooner propoſed it to him, than he readily complied with it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Hence, to the firm and immutable conſtituting of the Son of God a Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the <hi>Decree,</hi> there paſt an Eternal <hi>Tranſaction</hi> between the Father and him, which is beſt ſhadowed to us, by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Covenant:</hi> and becauſe it had a proper reſpect to the Ranſoming of his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170983:19"/> Choſen from ſin and miſery, it may there fore well be called the <hi>Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> If the Son of God became a Redeemer by his own Conſent freely, and was determined unto it before the World began, it infers, according to our Capacity, that there was ſomething pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him, and that he did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly accept of it.</p>
            <p>The Tranſactions between the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Divine Perſons; Infinitely Tranſcend our Underſtandings: but if we will form a Conception of them, it muſt be after this manner: and God is pleaſed ſo to declare it unto us, that we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to entertain it in our <hi>Faith;</hi> and in as much as this ſtands among the <hi>Decrees</hi> of God, in which there is the whole I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea of this work, and it is in all of it ratified unchangeably; there muſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the mention of all thoſe things which relate to it, be alſo a final and determinate concluſion about it; all muſt be ratified. In this regard the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Peace</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>between them both,</hi> Zech. 6. 13. hereupon alſo, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of it by the Father to the Son, is repreſented under the form of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Hypothetically</hi> propounding both a <hi>Condition</hi> and a <hi>Reward</hi> Iſa. 53. 10. and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170983:19"/> in Pſal 110. 7. there is a Connexion which amounts to the ſame thing, for in a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate Axiom,</hi> where there are things joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, that are conſequent the one upon the other, it bears the force of a <hi>Connex;</hi> and ſo it is in the Text; and this may ſuffice for the evidence of the thing, or that there is ſuch a Covenant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>Of the Parties in the Covenant of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT follows now that we come a little nearer, &amp; make a more diſtinct Survey of this Covenant, according to the Light afforded us concerning it in the Word of God. I ſhall therefore here explain it in ſuch things wherein the ſpecial na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, and its difference from other Covenants may be diſcerned; eſpecially the <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant of Grace;</hi> and here may theſe things be Enquired into.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Who are the Parties in this Covenant?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Whence this Covenant had its riſe, or what was the ground of its being made?</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170983:20"/>
               <item> 3. <hi>When it was made?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Whether it be a Covenant of Works or of Grace?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Who are Covenanted for?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>What are the Articles of it?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Who are the Parties in this Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a general Obſervation that in all Covenants there are two Parties, and there can be neither leſs or more; for the notion of a <hi>Covenant</hi> belongs to the Head of <hi>Relation,</hi> which hath but the <hi>Relate</hi> and the <hi>Correlate,</hi> and cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. If then there are divers parties, they ſuppoſe divers Covenants. In the Covenant of Works, God and Man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately were the Parties: In the New Covenant they are God and Man, thro' the Interpoſition of a Mediator, unto whom both Parties have a reſpect. But in the Covenant of Redemption they are <hi>God &amp; the Son.</hi> This is agreed on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all thoſe that acknowledge ſuch a Covenant, but under what conſideration, it is debated with reference to each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and may be here particularly Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plained.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is one Party, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 3. <hi>I have made:</hi> The Party that ſpeaks there is God himſelf. But it may be asked, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be to be conſidered <hi>Eſſentially</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170983:20"/> or <hi>Perſonally;</hi> and ſo is to be applied to the <hi>Father?</hi> In the former Deſcription given of this Covenant, I have expreſſed it as belonging to God the Father. There are ſome Divines who would have it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Eſſentially,</hi> and aſſigned to the <hi>Deity,</hi> conſidered in the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and not in any particular <hi>Subſistence,</hi> leſt otherwiſe the Holy Spirit, the Third Perſon in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Trinity ſhould be excluded from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſonally concerned in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. This Debate needs not be eagerly purſued, being eaſily reconcileable: here then obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Decree in which this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is to be found, is properly an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Act, or belongs to all the Three Perſons in common, as they are one in the Eſſence. Acts properly perſonal are only ſuch as flow from their <hi>Relative Properties,</hi> or at leaſt have their <hi>Foundation</hi> in theſe <hi>Relations.</hi> The Decrees is an act of Divine Counſel, exerted by the Divine Will, which is undivided, and common to the three perſons: and thus the Deity is the one party Covenanting, becauſe <hi>the Eſſential acts of the Trinity are undivid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Joh.</hi> 5. 17, 19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in theſe <hi>Eſſential</hi> Works, the Scripture frequently obſerves a <hi>perſonal</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170983:21"/> propriety, and an order of working ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of their Subſiſtence and manner of working: ſo that in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever work, any one perſons order of Subſiſtence, and manner of working doth principally appear, it is, by way of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialty, aſcribed to that perſon; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that perſon is alone in it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God doth herein manifeſt himſelf to us moſt clearly in ſuch a manner of being or <hi>Subſistence.</hi> The Father is the firſt Perſon, hence <hi>beginning</hi> Works are Attributed to him, as <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</hi> The Son is the Second Perſon, and therefore ſecondary works are aſcribed to him, ſuch as <hi>Redemption.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt is the Third and Laſt Perſon, and therefore finiſhing works are given to him, ſuch as <hi>Application.</hi> The Father works of himſelf, by the Son and Spirit. The Son works from the Father by the Spirit. The Holy Ghoſt works from them both; <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 19. 16. 13. and this Order is to ſhew the <hi>Oecononomy</hi> of the Divine Perſons. Now in this regard, Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Works may have a peculiar Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation to a perſon not excluſive, but incluſive of the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Jeſus Chriſt in making mention of this Covenant, acknowledgeth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170983:21"/> to be the Party whom he had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented withal. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 7, 8. the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of the Son here ſpoken to, and owned, points us to the Father under the <hi>Perſonal Relation.</hi> So alſo in Pſal. 89. 26. which <hi>Pſalm</hi> hath a proper reference to this Covenant; and how often in the Goſpel have we Chriſt declaring his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be from his <hi>Father?</hi> more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in <hi>John</hi> 17. he challengeth of him the performance of the Promiſes of this Covenant, and truly, as this Covenant is the beginning of all our Salvation, and the ſpring or Original from which all the good that we hope for, ſo it is fitly attributed to him, who is the firſt of the perſons.</p>
            <p>2. The other Party is the Son of God, the Second Perſon in the Trinity, who is Coeternal with the Father. The Covenant being Eternal, there could not be any party in it, but one who was an <hi>Eternal Perſon.</hi> Whoſoever is engaged in a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which is a voluntary act, muſt be preſumed to <hi>Exiſt,</hi> either in himſelf, or in his <hi>Repreſentative.</hi> Nor is this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted whether the Son of God be the other party: but yet there is no little difference in the notions about the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or reſpect in which he ſtands as a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170983:22"/> party in this Covenant. The Son of God is conſidered under a treble notion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Meerly as he is a Divine Perſon, and ſo is only <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As he hath aſſumed our Nature into Union with his Perſon, and ſo is <hi>God-Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As he hath a Myſtical Union with all the Members of his Church, or with all Believers, in which ſenſe he is alſo called <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 12. and under which of theſe conſiderations, he is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Covenant, is variouſly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. Here then we may conclude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt Myſtical is not the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this Covenant; my meaning i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that the Members of Chriſt, or his Spiritual Seed, were not joyntly Covenanters with him here. The People of God are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as a party in the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> with whom God Indents through a <hi>Mediator:</hi> but they have no ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration here. It is true, they are taken notice of in this Covenant, yea, it is for them that Happineſs was contrived and ſecured in it, but that is as they ſtand related to the Terms of it. The Elect are not <hi>Agents,</hi> but <hi>Patients</hi> here. There is nothing in it required of them to be done <hi>by them,</hi> but all is to be done <hi>for</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170983:22"/> 
               <hi>them.</hi> They are not <hi>Undertakers,</hi> but are <hi>Undertaken</hi> for, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 10. and this is one difference between theſe two Covenants.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence it is the Perſon of Chriſt alone that is the Party. It muſt be either Chriſt <hi>perſonal,</hi> or Chriſt <hi>Mystical:</hi> not the latter as is already declared. He was alone in this Undertaking. He only was to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the work of Redemption, and had no Coadjutor, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 3. Redemption-work is appropriated to him. As he was to have the whole honour of our deliverance paid unto him, ſo that none might ſhare with him in the Glory of it, he took none into Partnerſhip with him in the work, but took it wholly upon himſelf: nay there was none in Heaven or Earth to be found to Undertake in this Buſineſs beſides him, and therefore he ſtood alone in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt meerly conſidered as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Son of God, and the Second Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Bleſſed Trinity; and not as God and Man, by the Aſſumption of our Nature, is the other party in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. I know there are weighty Divines of another Perſwaſion, who labour by many arguments to prove that the Son of God, was looked upon as in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or with reſpect to the <hi>Futurition</hi> of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170983:23"/> his aſſuming it, in the Indenting of this Covenant: But I ſuppoſe that conception will overthrow the very notion of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in this matter. The preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion that hath now been laid down, will be apparent by theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is (as hath already been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) called a Covenant only by way of <hi>Analogy,</hi> as it is accommodated to our underſtanding; it being nothing elſe but that <hi>Article</hi> in the <hi>Decree,</hi> which concerns the <hi>Redemption</hi> of Man by Chriſt. There muſt therefore be ſuch an <hi>Analogy</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our conceptions of it, and it muſt be Interpreted by notions proper to a <hi>Covenant.</hi> Now, though the Father and the Son be one in <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and ſo have not two Wills, but one undivided; yet they are Two Perſons, and as ſuch, are conceived by us as conſulting, deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and concluding about things: hence the Divine Perſons are ſo repreſented, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. and the reaſon of it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the things done are, to our manner of conception, the Fruits of Counſel. That there was not only a Divine Will in the Father ſending, but alſo in the Son conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſent by him, we muſt needs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain; elſe we can have no rational and regular notion of a perſon ſending, and of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170983:23"/> a Perſon ſent. Although theſe are but one Will, yet it comes under a diſtinct conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by us, though the manner of it be above our conception.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt, not only as he is Man, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as he is Son, is in the <hi>Oeconomical</hi> Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of things, <hi>Subordinate;</hi> to his Father. Though in the Divine Eſſence he is Equal as he is God, (for, where there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat ſameneſs, there muſt needs be a perfect equality) yet in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Affairs of his Kingdom, he is Subordinate; The meer <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of our <hi>Humanity</hi> did not make him ſo; for his Perſon was not degraded by his <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> he was ſtill, in regard of that, <hi>In the Form of God, and counted it no Robbery to be Equal with him,</hi> Phil. 2. 6. but he volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily complied with his order. This is the common conſent of Orthodox Divines, and that according <hi>to Scripture,</hi> Gal. 14. 29. <hi>My Father is greater than I.</hi> Not as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he is God, for ſo he aſſerts, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 30. <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and I am one;</hi> but as he is the Father; conſidering Chriſt, not as man, but as Son. For this reaſon he is ſaid to be <hi>Sent</hi> by the Father: which muſt needs have reference to the Eternal Covenant; and that this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to his Perſon, therein appears, becauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170983:24"/> how elſe can we Terminate the <hi>Incarnation</hi> upon the Son, as the Perſon aſſuming.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though it be true, that without the Humane Nature Aſſumed by the Son of God, the work of Redemption could not have been performed by him (which is the main ſtreſs of the reaſonings for the other aſſertion) yet the Son of God both could and did undertake for the doing of this work, without the Humane Nature Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. The Incarnation therefore of the Son of God is rather a <hi>Condition</hi> of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, or a thing requiſite in him who was to be a Redeemer, in order to his fitneſs to go through with that great Undertaking; than a <hi>quality</hi> needed to render him a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Though the Son of God could not actually Redeem us, but in our Nature; yet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without our Nature he could Covenant to Redeem us. Though he could not perform Obedience, active or paſſive, to the Law, but in our Nature; which was only concerned in this Obedience, as to the actual performance of it, yet he could Undertake without it, to obey the Law in it; and that is ſufficient with reſpect to his Covenanting about it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Son of God became man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Covenant;</hi> and therefore is not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be conſidered as man in the act of <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170983:24"/> The Incarnation of the Son of God was one <hi>Article</hi> in this Covenant, as will be afterwards obſerved; it was one of the things undertaken by him, and for which he engaged. The futuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore of his being man depended upon this propoſal and undertaking; and for that reaſon muſt needs preſuppoſe it. Nor was it neceſſary that the perſon Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting muſt ſo be looked upon as man, for the Saving of the Elect before his actual coming in the Fleſh; it was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that the perſon was deſigned to this before time by promiſe or Covenant.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Covenant of Redemption was an <hi>Eternal Covenant;</hi> and therefore the party as ſuch muſt come under an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal conſideration, and that could only be in regard of his being the Eternal Son of God, or with reſpect to his Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonality. Though in the Decree, Chriſt is no ſooner appointed to be a Redeemer than he is deſigned to be man, and therefore this alſo had an Eternal conſideration in that; becauſe the Decree was <hi>from Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> and though in Eternity there be no <hi>Priority</hi> or <hi>Posteriority</hi> of time; for that would be to confound <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Eternity:</hi> yet in the things themſelves, there may be conſidered a priority and Poſteriority of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170983:25"/> 
               <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Order.</hi> Thus the cauſe is in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature before the effect: thus the Perſons Covenanting are in order before the Covenant it ſelf: and hereupon the <hi>Undertaking</hi> of the Son of God to be man, is in order before the <hi>futurition</hi> of his <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> It hath a Cauſal Antecedency to the futurity of this Aſſumption, becauſe that which made it future from Eternity, was the Compact which paſt between his Father and him about it in the Days of Eternity.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 5. <hi>Of the Riſe of this Covenant, or the Grounds of its being made.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT now follows, in the next place, that we enquire, <hi>from whence this Covenant had its Riſe,</hi> or what was the ground of the making of it.</p>
            <p>This will be beſt underſtood by our care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obſerving where this Covenant is pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced; and that is under the head of <hi>Election</hi> and it refers unto the <hi>means</hi> which were in it Ordained for the accompliſhment of it in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170983:25"/> the Salvation of ſuch as were Choſen. In the Decree (as in the prudent purpoſes of all wiſe Agents) there is the reſolving of the End, and the laying out of the means by which it is to be advanced. Theſe are inſeparable in <hi>Gods Purpoſing,</hi> but diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the <hi>things purpoſed.</hi> In the Decree we find ſuch a thing as <hi>Election,</hi> wherein God hath appointed men unto Salvation, and alſo contrived the way in which he will accompliſh it; and to this way doth the <hi>Covenant of Redemption</hi> appertain: and therefore the riſe of it was the <hi>meer good Pleaſure of God, to advance the glory of the Riches of his Grace, by the Redemption of his Choſen, and bringing of them to Enjoy Eternal Life;</hi> for which end, he appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his own Son to be the Redeemer, and Indented about it in a free Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Here let it be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That a Covenant is not a <hi>Natural</hi> but a <hi>voluntary</hi> act. In every Covenant there is a conſent of the parties Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting, to the Articles upon which it is built. Now conſent is performed by the Will: and therefore there was no natural neceſſity of any ſuch Contract as this between theſe glorious Perſons: ſo that it was Gods meer good pleaſure that gave
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170983:26"/> Being to it. The very thing about which it is concerned was arbitrary with God. There was no neceſſity lying upon him to ſave any of the race of fallen man, who had by their own fault deſtroyed themſelves: and therfore there could be no neceſſity lying upon him to contrive and fix a way in which this ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was to be brought about. God doth nothing <hi>neceſſarily</hi> but what he doth <hi>naturally</hi> all his other acts are free. <hi>Election is a voluntary thing.</hi> Eph. 1 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The conſideration when this Covenant paſt, tells us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t there could be nothing in the Creature to move theſe glorious perſons to indent it. It muſt be meer good pleaſure and nothing elſe, whatſoever can be ſaid of the creature which men can ſuppoſe to have argument in it to move towards ſuch a thing, is Poſteriour to, and Conſequent upon the Decree, to which this Covenant belongs. The object of it was a poſſible being; which as it had no being in it ſelf, ſo was here ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to have a being, and to paſs through all theſe changes that have befallen it, being Predeſtinated thereunto. So that we can look at no conſideration on this account, but what falls behind of having any poſſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into the Covenant. Not the ſtate of integrity, in which man was at firſt; for in that ſtate, had he continued in it, he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170983:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> had not needed a Redeemer. Not the miſerable Eſtate he fell into by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy; for, though that was a ſtep towards his Redemption, becauſe it put him into a capacity for it, and brought him under a neceſſity of it; yet it could not put God upon thinking of his Recovery; becauſe his Miſery was deſerved, and the Juſtice of God was concerned in it: and beſides, this fell under the Decree of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as a <hi>Medium</hi> towards the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods rich mercy in ſaving him. Not the previſion of any good nature or inclination in him; for there is not any ſuch thing truly in any ſinner by nature, nor the leaſt <hi>diſpoſition</hi> towards the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of this Redemption on <hi>Goſpel-terms,</hi> unleſs God do work it in him: nor is this always wrought in ſuch as are ſuppoſed to be naturally beſt inclined, but at Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 18. God therefore could have nothing out of himſelf to move him.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The ultimate end of Gods deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in this Covenant, was the Illuſtration of the Glory of his Rich Grace in them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at are ſaved, ſo we are told. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 6. God is his own laſt end in all his works of Efficiency, and therefore had that ultimate reſpect in all his Decrees. There are ſeveral reſpects
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170983:27"/> to his Glory which his ſeveral Works do bear: that of Fallen Mans Salvation was peculiarly deſigned for the Exaltation of the <hi>Praiſe of his Grace:</hi> That this Article might have a ſpecial manifeſtation by it. Hither then Election had an eye, and conſequently, all the Contrivances that were laid for the bringing about of the Salvation to which men were Elected, were meaſured accordingly. Infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſought out the beſt way to make this <hi>Attribute</hi> to ſhine in its Luſtre ſo as might be <hi>admirable;</hi> and it contrived this, which is ratified in this Covenant.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe there was a wonderful <hi>Love</hi> at work in it, to thoſe that were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed; hence the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is;e of this Covenant may well be aſſigned to the <hi>love of God</hi> which he bare from Eternity to his Elect. He Choſe them, and ſo Covenanted with his Son that he ſhould Redeem them; and why did he ſo? it was <hi>becauſe he loved them.</hi> The reaſon of this love is his good pleaſure. The firſt act wherein this love was expreſt, was in Chuſing us in Chriſt, and Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him to Redeem us; in which he laid a ſure and firm foundation for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: Gods ſending of Cbriſt is for this reaſon aſcribed to his unparalell'd love <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 16. 1. <hi>Joh</hi> 4. 10.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170983:27"/> 5. That which ſtreins this love up to the higheſt degree, is that it was a free and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate act, both on the part of God the Father deputing, and of God the Son ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting and undertaking in this buſineſs, we cannot conceive how there ſhould be any other way in which grace could poſſibly more ſhine forth than in Chriſt's Coming upon mans neceſſity, to do and dy for him. <hi>A greater love than this</hi> cannot poſſibly be thought of, than that God ſhould not <hi>ſpare His Own Son,</hi> &amp; that Chriſt ſhould not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold himſelf. The Apoſtles argument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes this to be the greateſt gift, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 32. Now the putting of this into a Covenant addes Emphaſis to it: that it ſhould not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be thought of, but indented for, and firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ratified in an Everlaſting and unchanga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Compact: that thus the ſinners eternal ſalvation ſhould be made ſure againſt all that might be ſuppoſed to offer to prevent it. It was therefore that <hi>Grace</hi> might appear to be <hi>Grace</hi> indeed, and his love might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us as moſt ſurprizing, that he put it into ſuch a method, which <hi>Infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> concluded upon as moſt proper to ſet it off by: and therefore, when God would call us to the contemplation of his great love to us, he leads us up thus far. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 3.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170983:28"/>
            <head>CHAP. 6. <hi>When this Covenant was made.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE next enquiry is when this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made? This queſtion ſeems to be here ſuperfluous, ſince we have already taken notice that it was an Eternal Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action: and being <hi>before time,</hi> it muſt needs alſo be <hi>without beginning:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt therefore ſpeaking of this deſign, ſaith, <hi>I was ſet up from Everlaſting,</hi> Prov. 8. 23. and for this reaſon it is ſaid of him, that he was <hi>Foreordained before the Foundation of the World,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 20. It was agreed upon <hi>before time</hi> was between God the Father and the Son, that he ſhould <hi>in time</hi> accompliſh the Salvation of the Elect; but yet becauſe, though in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Acts there is no ſucceſſion, yet, as we before obſerved, there is an order, it may not be unprofitable to conſider in what order this Covenant ſtands, and that for two reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe of the <hi>Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apſarians,</hi> who though they acknowledge the Eternal
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170983:28"/> Predeſtination of men to an Everlaſting State of Happineſs or Miſery, do yet place it in order after mans <hi>Apostaſy,</hi> and build it upon that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe of the forementioned Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe who preſuppoſe the Decree of Chriſts Incarnation, in order to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Covenant with him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as God and Man; wherein they do evidently make that Decree <hi>Antecedent</hi> to, and wholly <hi>distinct</hi> from this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Both of theſe do certainly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place the Covenant, and give it a wrong ſtation.</p>
            <p>As to the former of theſe it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to make theſe few Remarks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he who will rightly conceive of a Decree, muſt reduce all that refers to it to the two heads of <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> There is nothing that belongs to any Purpoſe, but it is either the thing purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or the way in which it is to be compaſſed: and therefore one of theſe two will take in whatſoever can be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned concerning it. But this is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple againſt which I apprehend no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional objection can be made, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to the common ſentiments of Mankind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Gods deſign in his Decree
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170983:29"/> was his own Glory; and that which Election had a peculiar reſpect to, was the Glory of his Grace. All Gods works of Efficiency were to ſet forth his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and thereby exalt his <hi>Declarative Glory;</hi> which he accordingly diſpoſed in his Eternal Decree, and hath a reſpect to in his Efficiency, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 4. In the choiſe which he made of men to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he contrived the advancement of that precious Attribute of Grace. This is pointed to as the end of all, Eph. 1. 4, 5, 6. <hi>It was to the praiſe of the Glory of his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the object of this Decree was <hi>Ens poſſibile,</hi> a poſſible Being. All Beings are either the firſt, or from the firſt. The firſt Being can be but one, and that is God. He only enjoyed a never Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning Eternity; all other are the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of time, before which they had no Exiſtence: and becauſe they were to be from him, not by any neceſſity, but by a voluntary act, hence, God being a Cauſe by Counſel in all his free and tranſient acts, there muſt a Purpoſe paſs with him in order to their Being: <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent</hi> to which purpoſe, in our concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there could be no other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the thing but as a <hi>meer poſſibility</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170983:29"/> for it was by vertue of this purpoſe that it Paſt into a <hi>Futurition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 All therefore that concerns this poſſible being in order to its reaching the deſigned end, belongs to the means. Hitherto, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Subject under our preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, viz. man, refer; <hi>His Creation; the ſtate of integrity in which he was made; the Covenant of works which God put him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; the permiſſion of the Apoſtaſy by which he fell under the Curſe of that Covenant, and ſo came to stand in need of Redemption.</hi> Either theſe things belongs to the Decree, or elſe there was no Decree about them; and ſo they fell out beſides Gods intention; or elſe we muſt aſſign two Decrees to God, and ſo two ends, and two orders, of <hi>Media</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the ſame <hi>Subject;</hi> and ſo we muſt ſuppoſe that God loſt his end in the Firſt, which put him upon a new contrivance in the latter. How unbecoming it is to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch conceptions about the great God, let any Chriſtian Judg. If then they apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Decree, it muſt be either to the end or the means: not to the end, for that is the glory of Grace, which is not the things themſelves, but that which Reſults from them: they then are but ſteps to it, and ſo muſt be of the means.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All the <hi>means</hi> as they refer to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170983:30"/> are <hi>Coordanate.</hi> In the <hi>execution</hi> indeed they are <hi>Subalternate,</hi> but not ſo in the <hi>purpoſe:</hi> I mean that though they are put into an order in the Decree, yet in the act of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creeing they are all together. They are a Chain linked in one, and do all together make but one entire Medium; nor can we rationally conceive them to be here ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. If we conſider the Permiſſion of Man to fall, antecedent to the Future Coming of Chriſt to Redeem him, we can in no ſence allow it to be a deſigned medium of the exaltation of free grace. If we conſider of Chriſt as appointed to the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, without the conſideration of Mans Apoſtaſy, we cannot conceive what he ſhould come for. And for this reaſon the <hi>Covenant of Redemption</hi> cannot in order follow the Decree of permitting man to fall, but muſt be together with it.</p>
            <p>As to the Second, let it be remembred, that it hath already bin made to appear, that the Covenant was made with the Second Perſon, and that his <hi>Incarnation</hi> was one thing put into the Covenant: ſo that it was this Covenant which gave Futurition to it: and therefore to ſuppoſe a <hi>Dtcree</hi> for the ſon of God to become man, antecedent to, and diſtinct from this Covenant, is not only <hi>Superfluous;</hi> for what need is there of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170983:30"/> two acts to paſs for one and the ſame thing? but it is indeed to <hi>vacate the very Notion of the Covenant,</hi> by taking away the whole that belongs to it, and aſſigning it to a Decree ſuppoſed to be diſtinct from it: for if we look upon Chriſt as God-Man, or Decreed to be ſo, we muſt conceive that he hath voluntarily Undertaken it, for he was not ſo neceſſarily: and then we muſt alſo ſuppoſe it was for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and that muſt be in order to his being a <hi>Redeemer;</hi> for on no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count did he ever deſign it: and if this be the <hi>Covenant it ſelf,</hi> how ſhould it be before it? Beſides, the <hi>Decree</hi> being (as hath already been obſerved) not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal but eſſential act, we may therefore ſafely and intelligently ſay, <hi>That one God in Three Perſons, in Decreeing of the means of mans Salvation, stated and ratified this Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170983:31"/>
            <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>Whether it be a Covenant of Works, or of Grace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT may furthermore be Enquired, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Covenant of Redemption is to be accounted a Covenant of Works, or of Grace; and here let me premiſe: That it is certainly a <hi>Covenant distinct</hi> from both of thoſe which ordinarily come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe Denominations among us. It is neither that which was made with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> in <hi>Innocency;</hi> nor that which is made with us in and through a <hi>Mediator,</hi> for in both of theſe man is of one party; whereas he is not ſo in this, but only a Subject in reſpect of which it is made: But if the enquiry be, under whether of theſe conſiderations it is to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in it ſelf, it may be readily replied, that according to its reſpects, it may be accounted either the one or the other. Here then we are to look upon it, either with reference to the <hi>matter</hi> of it, and the <hi>terms</hi> between the parties, or to the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>deſign</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170983:31"/> 1. If we conſider the <hi>matter</hi> of it, and the <hi>terms</hi> which were agreed on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parties Covenanting, it fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to a <hi>Covenant of Works;</hi> and indeed it bare a proper reſpect to the Covenant of Works which paſt between God and man at firſt. for Chriſt was to be the <hi>Second Adam;</hi> and therefore he was to do that for us which the other failed of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to reſtore us from that miſery, which he by his failure brought upon us: hence that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 22. <hi>As in Adam all dy even ſo in Christ ſhall all be made alive.</hi> But yet it was not the ſame Covenant with that; not only becauſe he was a <hi>diverſe party,</hi> but alſo becauſe he was <hi>differently concerned:</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> was only to obtain the Bleſſing by his <hi>Active Obedience,</hi> and to fall under the Curſe by his <hi>Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and that irrecoverably as to any power in himſelf, whereas the Son of God was to merit by his <hi>doing,</hi> and to make Satisfaction by his <hi>Suffering.</hi> But yet it ran in the tenor of a <hi>Covenant of Works,</hi> in which there is a work to be done, and a Reward to be given on the account of it. He was to purchaſe and pay for what he had, and that to the full price: on which account the <hi>Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>Purchaſed,</hi> Eph. 1. 14.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170983:32"/> and he is ſaid to <hi>give himſelf a ranſom,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim</hi> 2. 6. but this will be more fully ſpoken to, with the reaſon of it hereafter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider the end and whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of this Covenant, it iſſues in being a <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> Though it were ſo laid that <hi>Grace</hi> might appear conſiſtent with <hi>Justice,</hi> and therefore there was a work to be done for the making way for it, yet it carried Grace in the aim of it, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The laſt end of it was for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Rich Grace. Eph.</hi> 1. 5. 6. and the very Satisfaction made unto Juſtice in order to it, puts a great luſtre upon this Grace, in as much as Chriſt was to remove that obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle out of the way by his obedience which mans ſin had thrown into it. It was that God might expreſs his free and undeſerved favour to a number whom he had Choſen to be made partakers in it: that he might beſtow upon man a <hi>Salvation</hi> which he never <hi>Laboured for;</hi> bring him to an <hi>heaven</hi> he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>earned;</hi> enrich him with a <hi>portion</hi> which he could never have <hi>Purchaſed;</hi> and free him from a <hi>Miſery</hi> which would elſe have <hi>Swallowed</hi> him up for ever, &amp; which he had <hi>Procured</hi> to himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence all the means which were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon between theſe parties for this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170983:32"/> end, were the contrivances of this <hi>Grace.</hi> The whole Plot was ſo laid out, that in all of it there ſhould be the Beams of <hi>Divine-Love and Favour</hi> ſhining forth: for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The whole proviſion of a Redeemer was of <hi>Grace:</hi> whether we conſider it on the Fathers part <hi>Propoſing</hi> the thing, &amp; <hi>accepting</hi> of the way: He was under no neceſſity to offer ſuch a Propoſal; it was abſolutely free, yea, that he would be reconciled to ſinners in ſuch a way, was <hi>Grace</hi> The caſe is <hi>Criminal,</hi> man by his fall becomes a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent;</hi> Juſtice might have fallen upon him, and refuſed to have taken any other in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. Though the Satisfaction be valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough, yet the receiving it thus is <hi>voluntary,</hi> therefore it is <hi>Grace.</hi> Had God ſaid the ſinner himſelf ſhall Die, it had been juſt: or if we conſider it on the Sons part undertaking it; he had no obligation lying upon him by any kind of neceſſity; he was <hi>God bleſſed for ever</hi> before: his Divine Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Glory could not be augmented by it in the leaſt, he had no Conſanguinity to move him, for it was the Son of God that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted, he took up the kindred or relation by Covenant: ſee for this <hi>Phil</hi> 2. 6. 7. it was therefore of meer grace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The work it ſelf which he undertook to perform, conſidered with relation to this
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170983:33"/> thoſe for whom he was to do it, was alſo <hi>Grace.</hi> The Covenant of works requires of thoſe that are under it, either to <hi>Do</hi> or to <hi>Suffer:</hi> but that when we fell ſhort of doing, and have therby expoſed ourſelves unto Suffering, another ſhould interpoſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to do and Suffer for us, this it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires not. The Son of God was in himſelf naturally under no Law, and therefore his putting of himſelf into ſuch a condition as to be under it, and this that ſo he might do the greateſt kindneſs, muſt needs be of <hi>Grace;</hi> and that was the very deſign of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 8. <hi>God Commendeth his love, in that whiles we were yet ſinners, Chriſt Died for us. ſo, Gal.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>he was made of a woman, made under the Law, to Redeem them that were under the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 All the proffers of Salvation, which are in the Goſpel made unto Sinners, are the reſults of this Covenant: Here they have their <hi>Foundation.</hi> We find that all the good that is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndered to Fallen men in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> is offered <hi>freely.</hi> We muſt indeed come for it; but <hi>without money, and without price,</hi> Iſa. 55. 1. we muſt take it indeed, if we will have it, but it muſt be <hi>freely,</hi> Rev. 22 27. But whence is it that there are ſuch liberal offers made to the children of men? why it flows
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170983:33"/> from the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> and had it not been for this, there had never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ews been heard of in the World. Here was the Foundation laid for all the <hi>Saving Grace</hi> which is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed in time to any of the children of men; and ſo it muſt needs be a <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>Who are Covenanted for?</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Title put upon this Covenant, viz: of Redemption, ſuppoſeth a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> unto whom this <hi>Redemption</hi> is to be <hi>applied,</hi> and conſequently for whom it was <hi>undertaken.</hi> But it is requiſite that we Fix the due limits here, or elſe we ſhall be at a great loſs in an Eſſential Point relating un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Covenant, for only the Redeemed, and all of them are to receive the benefits of it; here then let theſe things be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſuppoſeth ſubject that ſtands in need of Redemption. To have undertaken it for any other, had been Supervacaneous. And
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170983:34"/> there could be no other ſuch monument but ſuch a creature as is forfeited, and fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to miſery, and cannot get out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it again, till it be bought out, and reſcued from it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are two ſorts of creatures that are reduced to this exigency, viz: <hi>fallen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men.</hi> As to the <hi>Angels</hi> which kept their firſt ſtation, though they needed <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,</hi> yet not <hi>Redemption:</hi> and that this Confirmation of theirs doth derive from this Covenant to them, is no-where in Scripture ſo much as inſinuated. But thoſe once <hi>Angels,</hi> now <hi>Devils</hi> are become miſerable by their woful revolt from God, being fallen under a Righteous Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore they ſo far need Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, as that without it they muſt needs be Eternally miſerable, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind are by the <hi>Apoſtaſy</hi> come under this infelicity: they are a company of <hi>dead Creatures,</hi> by vertue of that ſin, the Guilt whereof lieth heavy upon them, Rom. 5. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> or <hi>Devils,</hi> ſtand no way related unto this Covenant: but only men. God never thought of, or contrived a way for the Jayl-Delivery of Devils, but hath left them hopeleſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sentence which fell upon them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170983:34"/> when they rebelled againſt him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their miſery is beyond all hopes of remedy: they are ſaid to be <hi>Reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Everlaſting Chains,</hi> Jude, 6. But God had more Gracious thoughts for man: and in this reſpect we find, that the Son of God in purſuit of this Covenant, med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not with the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of the <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> nature, but took that only of <hi>Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Heb. 2. 16. And the reaſon of this was becauſe he had not covenanted to redeem <hi>Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but only <hi>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That all mankind univerſally were not included in this Covenant, ſo as that the Son of God undertook to pay the Redemption price for them. How far there was ſome benefit to redound from it to mankind, I here diſpute not: But that Chriſt became <hi>Surety</hi> to pay the <hi>Price</hi> for all, is not to be believed. As to the notion or diſtinction, of his redeeming all <hi>Sufficiently,</hi> and only ſome <hi>Effectually,</hi> it cannot be reconciled to ſenſe, how then ſhall it be believed? It is one thing to pay a Price of ſufficient value to redeem all, and another thing to pay it for their Redemption: and to ſuppoſe that he did it for this end, and yet they ſhould pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh at the laſt, is not only beſides, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture, Joh. 6. 39. <hi>This is the</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170983:35"/> 
               <hi>Fathers Will that hath ſent me, that of all that he hath given me, I ſhould Loſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> yea, if we conſider the nature of the Covenant, it will evidence it to be inconſiſtent. The end of it hath been ſhewn to be for <hi>the Glory of Gods Grace, in the Salvation of his Redeemed:</hi> this Covenant was a <hi>Medium</hi> to that end, and therefore all that were ſo Covenanted for muſt certainly attain it, or elſe the Covenant ſo far loſeth its deſign. This therefore is that which Chriſt Intercedes for in behalf of thoſe whom he hath Redeemed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 24. theſe are they whom <hi>his Father gave him,</hi> that he might Redeem them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That Thoſe whom he Covenanted for, were a Definite Company of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons. Not only was the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them agreed upon in this Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, but the individuals alſo were De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. Here obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Covenant did not run <hi>Illimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly.</hi> That he ſhould pay a price for all, and that offers ſhould be made to all, and that as many as would accept of them, might be made to partake in the benefits of it, was not the form in which this Covenant ran: There is indeed ſuch an offer made in the <hi>Promulgation</hi> of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170983:35"/> 
               <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> by the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to all unto whom it comes on ſuch a condition: but, neither is this to all men, nor yet doth the Covenant of Redemption run ſo. and there is this reaſon for it among others, becauſe it is one <hi>Article</hi> in this <hi>Covenant,</hi> that whom Jeſus Chriſt doth <hi>Redeem,</hi> he ſhall <hi>ſave,</hi> and in order to it bring them to himſelfe, <hi>John.</hi> 6. 37. and but for this, none would come to him, <hi>vorſe.</hi> 44. and then where would be the <hi>ſeed that ſhould ſerve him, and be counted to him for a generation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor did this Covenant run upon the <hi>Previous qualities</hi> of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n before Converſion. It did not ſay that ſuch ſorts of perſons ſhould be redeemed, and others not: but it took in, as God ſaw meet, all ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Jews and Greeks, Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> of every age, ſex and diſpoſition, ſome that proved civil before they were ſavingly changed; others who before they were brought home to Chriſt, were the vileſt and moſt debauched of mankind. This appears to have been ſo, by the event, for which we have plentiful Scripture Teſtimony; and therefore it aſſures us, that it was not upon theſe terms that it ſtood-</p>
            <p n="3">3. But it took in ſo many <hi>Individual</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, choſen according to the Sovereign pleaſure of God. Hither the Apoſtle limits
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170983:36"/> it, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 11. The <hi>Lambs Book of Life,</hi> in which <hi>names</hi> are <hi>written,</hi> mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 27. refers properly to this <hi>Covenant:</hi> and they are perſons who are <hi>written</hi> here; they have their <hi>names</hi> in it. The Son of God <hi>knew</hi> from eternity whom he was to Redeem, and God <hi>knew</hi> them. This is the <hi>Foundation</hi> of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, which hath ſuch a <hi>Seal</hi> upon it, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>who are his,</hi> this Indigitates the very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: Our <hi>Hygh Priest</hi> therefore had their <hi>names written upon his breſtplate</hi> when he was to offer the Sacrifice for them, and make expiation in <hi>their behalf</hi> in the <hi>Holy Place.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>What are the Articles of the Covenant?</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT Belongs to the nature of a Covenant that there are <hi>terms agreed</hi> upon, and <hi>concluded</hi> between the parties in it; or ſomething in which each obligeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the performance of: and by the diſtinct knowledge of theſe it is, that we come to have an inſight into the particular nature of any Covenant. It is therefore
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170983:36"/> needful that we take the account of the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Covenant of Redemption,</hi> that ſo we may diſcover the main and eſſential difference between that and the Covenant of Grace, to prevent our confounding of them one with the other. Here let it be obſerved that this is one of thoſe <hi>Covenants</hi> which is made between <hi>equals</hi> &amp; therein is divers from the other, which is made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>Superiour,</hi> and <hi>inferiour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> They are equal, whether we conſider them in their <hi>nature,</hi> Phil. 2. 6. or if we conſider the <hi>things ariſing from it;</hi> the Glory of One God in Three Perſons is the deſign which was laid in it: or if we conſider the <hi>mutual obligation:</hi> they ſtand equally bound each of them to the terms which he Undertakes. Now for a more diſtinct and particular view of theſe <hi>Articles,</hi> it may be Enquired,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>What were the common Terms between both the Parties?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>What were the Obligations lying upon each Party by himſelf?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What were the common Terms between both Parties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were ſuch as theſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That a certain number of Mankind ſhould be made the Monuments of Rich
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170983:37"/> Grace: or, That the Glorious Attribute of Grace ſhould be exalted in the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation of a <hi>Definite</hi> Company of men; and to this <hi>Article</hi> belongs the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of mans being <hi>Created in his Integrity; put under a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to fall from it, and make himſelf miſerable,</hi> in order to the making way for the Illuſtration of this Grace. That ſuch a thing ſhould be, was voluntary on Gods part, and therefore there paſt a Decree for it: and this being <hi>Eſſential,</hi> it belongs to all the Three perſons. Hence the Scripture ſpeaks of mens being <hi>Ordained</hi> or appointed to Glory, and of their being <hi>Elected</hi> or Choſen to the Kingdom: which expreſſions, denote this eternal deſignation, which was agreed upon, and ſo paſt between God, Father, Son, and Spirit; ſee' 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5, 9. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. 20. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 4. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 13. and all this was with an eye to the glorifying of the Grace of God, <hi>Eph</hi> 1. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That in order to the Illuſtration of this Grace in mans Salvation, the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant ſhould be Satisfied in all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of it, That whatſoever that required ſhould be fully reſponded. The conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans being under a <hi>Law-Covenant,</hi> and forfeiting himſelf to the <hi>Curſe</hi> of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuppoſed in the former <hi>Article;</hi> there is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170983:37"/> a Proviſo, that the Covenant ſhall not be baulked, and that therefore the Salvation intended ſhould make no breach upon, nor offer any violence to the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Justice;</hi> but that it ſhould in all points be complied withal, and mans Salvation be ſo effected as that no <hi>jot or tittle of the Law ſhould paſs:</hi> for ſo it is brought about <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 18. and that <hi>Justice and Peace ſhould agree in one, Pſal</hi> 85. 10. that <hi>God ſhould be Just in Justifying of the ſinner. Rom.</hi> 3. 26.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That in order to the accompliſhment of this great affair, there ſhould be a ſutable and ſufficient Redeemer provided, who ſhould undertake this work, and accompliſh it in all things that were requiſite for the compleating of it. The agreement about a Redeemer ſtill belongs to the common conſent among the three Divine Perſons, according to our diſtinct conception of it; for it is an act of abſolute Divine Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty to accept of Satisfaction at the hands of any beſides the proper Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the caſe being <hi>Criminal:</hi> it muſt therefore proceed from that Soveraign Will of his to determine that it ſhould be ſo, from whence alone it could be a thing acceptable to God, when therefore Chriſt appeared in the Execution of his Work, God declared his acceptableneſs to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170983:38"/> him by a <hi>voice from Heaven,</hi> Mat. 3. 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What were the Articles peculiar, or the Engagements lying upon each party by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such there were, and here in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral we are to obſerve: That though the Parties were equal in their <hi>Covenanting,</hi> yet in the <hi>Covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t;</hi> one Party Indented to be Inferiour to the other. The Son of God was to take to himſelf a Nature, in which he was to be his Fathers <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> hence he is ſo called, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 1. and becauſe there was ſomething to be done by him firſt, in order to his meriting of that which he was to receive of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for it; this may firſt come under our conſideration: Here then</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may conſider the Engagement which the Son took upon himſelf. The work of <hi>Redemption</hi> was laid upon his Shoulders, he was the party agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſenting to take that Province upon him in his own perſon: and it may ſuffice to ſpeak generally of this, and ſo his Undertaking may be compriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He accepted of and took upon him to perform the work of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and thereby he received the Relative Title of <hi>Redeemer</hi> from <hi>Eternity.</hi> To this the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170983:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> bears witneſs, when it tells us, that he was the <hi>Lamb ſlain from the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World, Rev.</hi> 13. 8. and when it ſaith that we are <hi>Choſen in him, to obtain Redemption by him,</hi> Eph, 1. 4, 7. which Scriptures clearly expreſs his deſignation to this Office <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Work, and this being perſonal, hence there was, not only the Father <hi>Propounding,</hi> but the Son alſo <hi>conſenting</hi> and <hi>accepting:</hi> ſo that this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts properly to one <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Covenant:</hi> for we cannot rationally ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a perſon free, ſovereign, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no natural obligation to it, to be deſigned, conſtituted, and ſet apart to an Office, without his own free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary conſent. Hereupon it follows, that on this very ſcore or account, all the <hi>old Teſtament</hi> believers, dying before his appearing in the fleſh, went to heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the credit of his undertaking; having their ſins diſcounted, and their happineſs conferred upon them, in the merit of that ſatisfaction and obedience which he had engaged for.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He undertook and engaged to do all that which was requiſite for the performance and accompliſhment of this Redemption, and this is neceſſarily inferred upon the former. He who takes upon him to do any
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170983:39"/> work, engageth himſelf to do all that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the work cannot be done. What this was will appear, both by taking a view of that which was needful for mans reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from miſery, and being reſtored to favour and happineſs; and by obſerving what it was that the ſon of God did actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally perform. Whatever Chriſt did go thorough here, was <hi>according to the foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and determinate Counſel of God.; i. e.</hi> the Covenant between God the Father and the Son: and this was ſummarily in two things</p>
            <p n="1">1 That he would aſſume to his perſon the nature of man, and thereby put himſelf into a capacity of performing Redemption work. That the Covenant was made with the Son of God not conſidered as God man, but only as Son, hath been already made to appear. This undertaking then is to be conſidered as an <hi>Article</hi> belonging to it, and it muſt needs be ſo, for the Son of God could not be appointed to be a Man but by a Covenant, becauſe his conſent was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely requiſite in ſuch an appointment, it being a Covenant between equals, as is granted on all hands: hence we muſt either unneceſſarily multiply Covenants, or elſe aſſign it unto this. The <hi>Scripture</hi> mentions no more but <hi>three covenants</hi> in which God is concerned about man; viz: that of <hi>works</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170983:39"/> that of <hi>Grace</hi> and this of <hi>Redemption;</hi> and it muſt belong to this, if to any of theſe; for in the other two, men themſelves are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Beſides, the Humane Nature to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed needs not to be reſpected as <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting,</hi> but only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Covenanted</hi> for, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the Divine Nature aſſuming the Humane, wrought it into a perfect ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to itſelf: for it was not to have an <hi>Humane Perſonality,</hi> but to be of the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the Son of God, and to be an organ or inſtrument in and with which the Son of God was to do this work. It was a body, <hi>i. e.</hi> (an Humanity) <hi>Prepared for him, Heb.</hi> 10. 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That in this nature he would become <hi>ſponſor</hi> or <hi>ſurety</hi> for Gods Elect, and ſo put himſelf under the law, and ſtand reſponſible to it for all that was demanded of them whether of <hi>active</hi> obedience as they were Gods <hi>ſubjects,</hi> or <hi>Paſſive,</hi> as they were <hi>ſinners.</hi> Hence that <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4. 5. He was not only to be in our <hi>nature,</hi> but alſo in our <hi>ſtead,</hi> he was to <hi>do</hi> that we might be happy, and to dy that we might be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from miſery. This is included in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 10. Thus he became a ſurety by way of exchange, not as bound joyntly with us, but as bound alone for us. Gods Holineſs did expect <hi>Obedience,</hi> and his Juſtice did exact <hi>Satisfaction</hi> from him upon our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170983:40"/> for this reaſon is he called, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Lamb,</hi> but a <hi>Lamb ſlain from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Rev</hi> 13. 8. for then was his death agreed upon and fully concluded: hence when they who were the inſtruments of it, had w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their malice upon him, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of God acquaints us that it was according to Appointment, a thing <hi>determined</hi> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 23. the whole work that Chriſt did upon Earth, was nothing elſe but a fulfilling of this Covenant: he did not do it by any compulſion, but volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily; ſo he tells us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 17, 18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The obligations which God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound himſelf in, in this Covenant, were of two ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as relate to Chriſts help and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement in the Undertaking and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the work of mans Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption: and theſe are principally three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Inveſting him with ſuch <hi>Offices</hi> as were needful for the diſcharge of this great Work. It was meet that the Son of God ſhould come with <hi>Authority.</hi> There were great things to be done in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Buſineſs; and the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of all depended on the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God: The <hi>Redeemer</hi> therefore muſt not only be <hi>deſigned</hi> but <hi>Inveſted.</hi> The Son of God was, in our Nature to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augurated</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170983:40"/> in his Mediatorly Function; hence his being <hi>Anointed King,</hi> was according to the <hi>Decree,</hi> Pſal. 2. 9, 8. and hereupon alſo he is ſaid to be an <hi>Everlaſting Prieſt,</hi> Pſal. 110. 7. and a deſigned <hi>Prophet,</hi> Iſa. 42. 6, 7. for theſe Prophetical Predictions concerning him were diſcoveries of the Tenour of this Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fitting of him for this work, with all the things which were requiſite for his being every way furniſhed for the diſcharge of it, elſe his Offices had been in vain. God is not wont to ſend a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger</hi> without Legs. If God <hi>calls</hi> any to ſpecial Service, he <hi>furniſheth</hi> him, and this was promiſed to the Son: he was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to have an Humane Nature <hi>Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically</hi> United to his Perſon, without which he could not have actually appeared in the Buſineſs of mans Redemption, or poſſibly have ſtood our Surety, according to the Tenour of the firſt Covenant. This is by a Synecdoche called a <hi>Body,</hi> and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſaid to prepare it for him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 5. and this refers to that ancient Covenant in which there was ſuch a proviſion made as is expreſt in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 7. He was alſo to have this Humane Nature fitted and qualified with all the neceſſary Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereby it might be capacitated
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170983:41"/> for the doing of what was requiſite, and to this end was his <hi>Unction</hi> promiſed, Iſa. 61 1, 2 whereby he was not only <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted</hi> in his Offices, but alſo his Humane Nature was <hi>Sanctified,</hi> and all thoſe Graces which were needful for him in his active and paſſive Obedience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere put into him in an overflowing meaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 34.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The affording to him all the ſupplies of all conſtant aſſiſtance in his Work, that ſo it might not fail in his Hand. It was a great work, and it was a frail na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in which it was to be performed; for this cauſe it would need mighty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to ſupport or uphold it ſo as not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ail. There was Infinite Wrath which our Nature was to ſuſtain, and therefore a <hi>mighty arm</hi> muſt be underneath to bear it up, el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it would have been broken in pieces by it. Almighty Power therefore did ſtand engaged for him, whereby a good iſſue of this Affair was ſecured. God promiſed him that he ſhould not ſink under the weight of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 21. Iſa. 42. 4, 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as relate to the Fruit and Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Undertaking: and theſe are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The acceptance that this work ſhould
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170983:41"/> find at the Fathers Hands. We have already obſerved, that not only the <hi>Valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs</hi> of the Satisfaction offered, but alſo the <hi>Acceptance</hi> of it with God, is to be conſidered in the making of it a <hi>Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption:</hi> becauſe it is at Gods liberty whether he will let the Priſoner of Juſtice go free, and receive another to ſtand in his room. Now God promiſed to his Son in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that he would take content in this Satisfaction of his; that it ſhould be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grateful or pleaſing thing to him; and accordingly it is expreſſed concerning him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reward which he ſhould receive for this work of his. There was a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Indented for, and Chriſt had an Eye to it in this Work, and Improved it for his Relief, when he was under the ſoreſt Agonies of Temptation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. and that was.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of himſelf perſonally; that he ſhould receive the higheſt honour and glory in our nature, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 27. this therefore was propounded after the nature of a reward, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 8, 9. Yea, ſuch a Reward is promiſed, as ſhall give him full content, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 11. we find that his Work and Recompence are put together, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. <hi>ult.</hi> He was to have
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170983:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Everlaſting. Honour of this Work aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to him, and to Triumph gloriouſly</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of thoſe who were to be Redeemed by him. As he <hi>Sanctified himſelf for their Sakes,</hi> and undertook to Redeem them by Satisfying for them, as a fruit of his Everlaſting Love to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Father promiſed him that he ſhould Enjoy them as a <hi>Purchaſe,</hi> and that they ſhould be a <hi>Generation</hi> of his <hi>Praiſe,</hi> Pſal. 22. 30. Iſa. 53. 10. He was aſſured that not one of all thoſe whom he was to Dye for, ſhould ever be Loſt, or finally miſcarry, but they ſhould all of them be brought to the Poſſeſſion of that Glory which he ſhould procure for them: that they ſhould be his <hi>Spouſe;</hi> and therefore we have him claiming this Reward, as that which he had Indented for, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 24. and theſe are the Summary Articles of this Wonderful Covenant.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170983:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>The neceſſity of this Covenant, in order to Mans Salvation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT may be enquired what ground there was for ſuch a Covenant as this? or, what reference Mans Salvation hath to it, and dependence upon it? and the enquiry into this will ſerve to ſet forth the Rich Grace of God to man, in thoſe Ancient Thoughts he had for him; and here in general it may be aſſerted, That there was a neceſſity for ſuch a Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to paſs. But that this neceſſity may be rightly ſtated; I ſhall firſt obſerve what ſort of neceſſity it is, and then clear it up.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A thing may be ſaid to be neceſſary in a double reſpect, <hi>viz. Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Hypothetical;</hi> and there is a great difference between theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Abſolute Neceſſity, which may alſo be called <hi>Natural,</hi> is ſuch as flows from the very nature and being of the thing.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170983:43"/> Thus we ſay the fire burns neceſſarily, becauſe it is a natural quality of it, and inſeparable from the form.</p>
            <p>Thus it is natural and neceſſary for God to Love Himſelf; for the Father to Beget the Son, for the Holy Ghoſt to proceed from them both. Whereas there are other acts of God which are not Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, but meerly voluntary; as the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the World, the making theſe and thoſe ſorts of Creatures, and many the like.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hypothetical or <hi>Conditionate</hi> Neceſſity is when upon the ſuppoſition of one thing to be done, there is ſomething neceſſary in order to it without which it cannot be done: ſo that though it be not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to do the thing, yet if he will do it, he muſt needs do thus or ſo in order to the accompliſhing of it; and this neceſſity flows from the <hi>connexion</hi> of things one with another. An end is not attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without the uſe of means; and there are means that are proper, on which the attaining of the end hath dependance, or without which it cannot be reached; ſo that if he will not miſs of his deſign, a perſon muſt neceſſarily uſe the means that are ſo connected unto it; and when there are various means or divers ways to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170983:43"/> the deſign, the neceſſity is more looſe and diſjunct, it being indifferent as to this or that, but yet it muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be one of them. But when the <hi>Medium</hi> is but one, it is then a reſtrained neceſſity; either this way or not at all. Now the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> under conſideration is not of the firſt ſort, or <hi>Abſolute,</hi> but of the Second, <hi>viz. Conditionate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For the more clearing up of this, let it be conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God was under no natural neceſſity to Save any of Fallen Mans Poſterity. There was no tie of Nature upon him, to give a pardon to, and beſtow Salvation upon any of that Ruin'd Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. He might have Damned them all, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any injury to himſelf, or wrong done to them; and that he did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o do, is a fruit not of <hi>Compulſion,</hi> nor of <hi>Nature,</hi> but of his meer <hi>Good Will,</hi> Rom. 9. 18. No man can give any other reaſon of the thing it ſelf, than that which he gives of the choice of the Subject in particular. The ſame reaſon why he chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this man, and not the other, is to be aſſigned why he chuſeth any at all, and that is, <hi>becauſe it ſo ſeemed good unto him,</hi> Mat. 11. 24. for they were all equally ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170983:44"/> 2. That hence God was not under any natural neceſſity of engaging in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for the bringing about the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of men. If the effecting of the thing were arbitrary to him, then the Indenting about the doing of it muſt needs be ſo too. If God might have left the whole Race of Mankind to have periſhed for ever; and that he doth not ſo do is <hi>contingent,</hi> i. e. <hi>free and voluntary;</hi> than whatſoever refers unto the deſignation or appointment of it in the Decree muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of his Will: and hitherto this Covenant is to be referred. Yea, indeed if it had been natural, the notion of a Covenant made about it had been impertinent; the fixing of a Decree concerning it, had been ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous; for what occaſion is there for a Decree about natural actions?</p>
            <p n="3">3. That natural Neceſſity deſtroys the very nature of a Covenant. For, a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is a voluntary obligation between perſons about things wherein they enjoy a freedom of Will, and have a power to chooſe or refuſe. It is a deliberate thing wherein there is a Counſel and a Conſent between Rational and free Agents. It is true, a perſon may be a Subject, and ſo under the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Conſenting</hi> in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170983:44"/> a Covenant; ſo was <hi>Adam</hi> at the Firſt: but ſtill the act of <hi>conſent</hi> it ſelf, is the act of a <hi>Cauſe by Counſel;</hi> and therefore it is not abſolutely neceſſary, ſo as that he could not but do it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether there be a natural or abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity, in regard of the Nature of Gods Juſtice and Holineſs, that there ſhould be a counterprice paid to make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for ſin, in order to the ſinners ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may be diſputed, I know this aſſertion is by ſome defended againſt the <hi>Socianians,</hi> &amp; as ſtifly denied by other who are no <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> &amp; ſuppoſe that there are other things in Scripture ſufficient to confute them. That becauſe God is naturally <hi>Holy</hi> &amp; <hi>Juſt,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt needs <hi>puniſh</hi> ſin either in the <hi>Sinner,</hi> or in his <hi>Surety,</hi> ſeems not to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident. To ſay that God could not by his abſolute Lordſhip have Saved a Sinner without a <hi>Mediator,</hi> looks as if it laid him under a neceſſity beyond what the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will warrant. It is true;</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Holineſs and Juſtice are Divine Eſſential Perfections. Every Attribute of God, is God diſplaying of himſelf to us after ſuch a manner: and though theſe are manifold as they come to our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, yet they are in him one and the ſame undivided Being. They are the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170983:45"/> things by which he maketh himſelf known to the Creature: and if he were not ſuch an one in himſelf they would be a falſe Repreſentation, which is blaſphemy to ſuppoſe. If there were no Creature to be the Subject of the Application of theſe, yet God would be, and is everlaſtingly <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Juſt:</hi> for if he will make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf appear to be ſo in his Works, it is becauſe he is ſo in his Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in all his Works of Efficiency, he aims at the Declaration of the Glory of his own Perfections. What elſe is the <hi>Declarative Glory</hi> of God, but a diſplay of his <hi>Eſſential Glory</hi> to the Creature, ſo far as he ſees meet? He had all in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before there was a World; but he would have a World to be a Mirrour of his Perfections; and thoſe to be in it who ſhould be able to read them, and acknowledge him therein; and therefore theſe are to declare it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. and he is ſaid to be <hi>known</hi> by them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That hence he contrived all in a <hi>con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecency</hi> for the expreſſing of his Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Natural Perfections, and that by his Infinite Wiſdom. It muſt needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and aſſerted, that God had a reſpect to thoſe <hi>Attributes</hi> of his, which he would make known to the World, in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170983:45"/> the laying out of all his Works of Ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiency in the <hi>Eternal Decree.</hi> Hence we have eminent diſplays of Gods <hi>Holineſs,</hi> in the Diſpleaſure that he diſcovers againſt Sin; and of his <hi>Juſtice</hi> in that he will not let it go unpuniſhed. He therefore orders his Works ſo as theſe ſhall have their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable manifeſtation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the nature of Sin, as Sin, moſt properly appears in that it is againſt God, and therefore cannot but be hateful to him in regard of his <hi>Holineſs.</hi> Holineſs is God bound for his own Glory, and therefore ſet againſt whatſoever ſtands in the way of it. We cannot then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, but that upon ſuppoſition of Sin <hi>committed,</hi> God is <hi>provoked,</hi> and cannot poſſibly approve of it, bat abhors i., <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That there is an eminent diſplay of Gods <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> in the witneſs which he bears againſt Sin, by reſolving to puniſh it either in the Sinner or his Surety. Certainly God doth herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be Glorious in Holineſs, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently Juſt. It gives a clear and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt declaration of it to the Conviction of all: and indeed, were it not for that it ſo doth, God would never have put things in this way; for the Affair was contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170983:46"/> for this very end: and Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold and unſearchable Wiſdom appears in his contriving theſe means, ſo admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuited to the advancement of his end, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 16.</p>
            <p>But that from hence the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of Sin with Eternal Death, proceeds from a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural neceſſity,</hi> is a further enquiry. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in deſerves it, is not to be doubted, but that God is naturally obliged to puniſh it ſo, and cannot be God unleſs he doth, needs further conſideration: and there are theſe things which may be thought of about it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Holineſs and Juſtice are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in Efficiency as <hi>Relative Attributes.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ivines diſtinguiſh of thoſe Attributes which appear to us in the conſideration of Gods <hi>Sufficiency;</hi> and thoſe that are diſcovered in his <hi>Efficiency.</hi> Theſe latter are called <hi>Relative,</hi> becauſe there is a <hi>Relation</hi> to the Creature evidently appears in the diſplay of them; and ſuch are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lineſs</hi> is ſeen in Gods managing all the Affairs of the Creature ſo as to gain Glory to himſelf by all. <hi>Juſtice,</hi> in Gods ſtanding by his own Law, and the terms of the Covenant which paſt between him, and Rational Beings: ſo that theſe do ſuppoſe the Reaſonable Creature
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170983:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> as the Subject in which they are mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſted, and a Tranſaction between God and them, as the ground of that proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and therefore the declaration or diſplay of them terminates on the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the puniſhment of Sin according to theſe, muſt alſo terminate on the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For God to <hi>Hate</hi> Sin, may be conceived to be in himſelf: but to <hi>puniſh</hi> it, muſt have a Subject on which it falls, and that is a Creature, who is puniſhed: and this proceeds from the <hi>Relative</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of theſe <hi>Attributes,</hi> with regard to the <hi>Declaration</hi> of them. <hi>Puniſhment</hi> is the Execution of a juſt Sentence unon a delinquent: and we may conceive <hi>Juſtice</hi> to be in God Eſſentially as a Perfection; and conſequently <hi>anger,</hi> which is nothing elſe but his juſt diſpleaſure at Sin: but not ſo <hi>puniſhment,</hi> which is a tranſient thing, and paſſeth on the Subject puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That hence <hi>puniſhment</hi> is to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to Gods works of <hi>Efficiency,</hi> of which the Rule given by Divines is, <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne opus ad extra eſt Contingens.</hi> That all Gods Acts or Works out of himſelf are Contingent, as they are oppoſed to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of nature; <hi>i. e.</hi> they might have
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170983:47"/> been, or they might not have been. That they are voluntary acts of Choiſe, and depend on his Will. Whatſoever concerns any Second Being, was at Gods pleaſure, as to his treating with it, and his Diſpenſations of himſelf unto it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence all the Works of Efficiency are the Executions of a <hi>Free, Decree,</hi> Eph. 1. 11. It refers to all Gods Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both of Creation and Providence: whatſoever God doth by neceſſity of nature, needed not to have paſt into a Decree. The Decree is acknowledged by all the Orthodox, to be a voluntary Deliberation and Determination of a moſt free agent, preſcribing to himſelf an <hi>Idea</hi> or method for the order and way in which he will carry on thoſe Affairs he intends to manage, and although there is a ſort of freedom which is conſiſtent with neceſſity; yet a thing cannot be both naturally <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and yet <hi>arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> becauſe theſe two are contradiſtinct.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There was Gods abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty or Lordſhip in making of the <hi>Decree.</hi> We may ſee Infinite <hi>Wiſdom, Holineſs, Juſtice, Grace,</hi> in the contrivance it ſelf: and reaſon good, for it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived on purpoſe for the Declaration of theſe: but in the contrivance it ſelf, his
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170983:47"/> Supream abſolute Liberty was aſſerted: and therefore the Apoſtle reduceth the anſwer to all the Diſputes and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſings of mens hearts, unto this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 20, 22. If God Decree, he cannot do it otherwiſe than as God; But yet he uſeth his holy pleaſure in it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the Puniſhment of Sin muſt have ſome referrence to the perſon, and terminate there. If we conſider Sin ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractly and ſeparately, as it is an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, we cannot conceive how or after what manner it can be puniſhed: The <hi>penalty</hi> of it therefore muſt bring it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conſideration of a <hi>Guilt</hi> which it leaves upon the Sinner, and by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of it expoſeth him to <hi>puniſhment.</hi> The Sinner is the guilty perſon, and the Sin is his, and therefore if Sin be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily puniſhed, it would conſequently follow, that the Sinner in perſon muſt be puniſhed, becauſe the Sin is his, and the ſpot of it cannot be Tranſlated. If then this Guilt may be removed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, it argues that there is an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarineſs in the puniſhing of it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Hence the transferring of the guilt and puniſhment of Sin from the Sinner to his Surety, ſeems to plead againſt this natural neceſſity: becauſe, if the penalty
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170983:48"/> be removed, the Offender may eſcape and therefore Sin may go unpuniſhed in him: and that God will not remove it from him but in a way of Tranſlation ſeems to be voluntary, becauſe he hath contrived it as a way moſt ſuitable to advance the Declarative Glory of his <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi> It is moſt certain, that Chriſt in ſuffering for Sin, ſuffered <hi>Arbitrarily;</hi> there was the higheſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty expreſſed in it. The pardoning of the Sinner hereupon is equally <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> and refers to the <hi>Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption:</hi> and how this ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with <hi>Relative Justice,</hi> except God had a Soveraignty in regard of the thing it ſelf, is very hard for any to tell.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> are alſo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections. Theſe are equally God with the other. They are Divine A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and are as much Eſſential to God, as his <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> though they are alſo <hi>Relative</hi> in the manifeſtation of them. When God ſhews himſelf merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and gracious in pardoning Iniquity, Tranſgreſſion, and Sin, he ſhews himſelf to be God, which he ſhould not do, if theſe were not his <hi>Innat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Perfections.</hi> Theſe are therefore <hi>Letters of his Name,</hi> Exod.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170983:48"/> 34. 6, 7. and by theſe he gives us to know him.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Hence we may ſeem to argue as ſtrongly, that God <hi>Pardons</hi> Sin by neceſſity of nature, as well as <hi>Puniſheth</hi> it. For ſurely he is gracious as well as Holy and Juſt; and then by conſequence God could no more have avoided pardoning than puniſhing of Sin: but we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that his Grace proceeds according to his good pleaſure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 18. 21, 22. Beſides, it is to be remarked that Gods <hi>Holineſs</hi> appears in the Illuſtration of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of his Attributes, and getting himſelf a Name thereby.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations ſeem to have their weight. But it muſt be confeſſed that Gods Judgments are a great deep, and Sobriety becomes us in our enquiry into the grounds and cauſes of them. Sin is nothing leſs becauſe God pardons it, and the neceſſity of the interpoſing of a Surety for the procuring of this pardon, will be built upon another ſure <hi>Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> which the Scripture is full for, and this leads to the next thing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Poſitively; there is a <hi>Connex</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Neceſſity of this Covenant, which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170983:49"/> we may take the account of in a few Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God, by his Relative Juſtice, ſtands firmly engaged to puniſh Sin. Here let it be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is a <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice appears in doing that which is right. There muſt be ſomething that muſt fix the bounds betwixt right and wrong, or elſe there is no ſcope for Juſtice to exert it ſelf. Juſtice appears in the manifeſtation of Gods Righteouſneſs: but that cannot be manifeſted, nor can the Creature be brought to confeſs it to him, in reſpect of his Works, but by being convinced that he doth that which is right: and that muſt be by reducing it to a <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> God in <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> may do what he will with the Creature; and that is <hi>Juſt</hi> in it ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he can do no wrong. But <hi>Justice</hi> is here conſidered in diſtinction from his <hi>Arbitrary Supremacy,</hi> and therefore muſt have reſpect to a Rule; this is implied, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Gods Decreeing Will is the Rule of his Relative Juſtice. The <hi>Decree</hi> laid out the <hi>Rule:</hi> for God is <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Law-giver.</hi> The Law of <hi>Gubernation,</hi> is the Rule of <hi>Government.</hi> Mens <hi>Laws</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170983:49"/> are called their <hi>Decrees,</hi> becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate about them, and then Decree them, and ſo make them authentick. Gods <hi>Decrees</hi> are <hi>Laws,</hi> becauſe in them he hath voluntarily determined how to Govern the Creature: and though his Wiſdom hath ſuited them to the natures of the Creatures to be Governed; whence the Light of Nature may make great diſcoveries; yet his <hi>Fiat</hi> makes them au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick: and there are ſome <hi>poſitive</hi> ones too. We Define Juſtice, to be a <hi>conſtant reſolution to do that which is right:</hi> now Gods Will is the meaſure of that which is right: and as in the Decree he laid out his <hi>own Efficiency,</hi> ſo alſo the <hi>Creatures Duty;</hi> and hither the Rule muſt refer. The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is his, and therefore he may preſcribe to it, and it ows him Obedience. It is therefore obſervable, how often when God publiſheth his Edicts, he gives no other reaſon for them, but, <hi>I am the Lord,</hi> q. d. it is my will and pleaſure, and who dares to Cavil at it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the firſt Covenant made with <hi>Adam,</hi> and the Law therein given him, was an <hi>expreſs</hi> of this Decree concerning the duty of men, and the rewards of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Sin. It was becauſe God had purpoſed thus to proceed with man, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170983:50"/> he publiſhed to him this Law, with the <hi>Sanctions</hi> of it; wherein he aſſured him, that if he obeyed he ſhould <hi>live,</hi> but if he tranſgreſſed, he ſhould <hi>die,</hi> Gen. 2. 17. and therefore what God hath ſaid on this account, he is reſolved to purſue it, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 4. This Tranſaction is repreſented under the notion of a <hi>Covenant,</hi> to ſignify that there was a <hi>mutual obligation:</hi> not only did God oblige man in it, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too; and here was, as it were, a publication of the Edict or Decree, that man might know what God was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on, and upon what ground he himſelf ſtood.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hence man by his fall coming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Law of Death, Juſtice is ſtrongly engaged to ſee the Law Executed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true intent of it. God having given to man a Law, according to which he was to ſtand or fall, he muſt in Juſtice judge him by the Law. Now Gods <hi>Holineſs, Juſtice, Truth, Righteouſneſs, Immutability</hi> ſtand all concerned in it. Upon this account, Chriſt aſſures us of the neceſſity that not one ſyllable, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or point of the Law muſt fall to the ground, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 18. yea, God himſelf ſwears that he will do Juſtice, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 40. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and indeed, becauſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170983:50"/> God was reſolved to make ſin a foil, on which he would draw the Colours of his Holineſs, in the diſplays both of his Juſtice and Grace, he therefore inviolably fixed this Law or Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That hence Relative Juſtice requires that if ſinning man be pardoned, his ſin muſt be ſatisfied for according to this Law, in a Surety. Here lies the ground of the neceſſity. If any ask, why need God to lay a ground for ſuch a neceſſity, if he could by his Lordſhip have pardoned Sin without a Mediator? it is eaſily replied, who are we to call him to an account? and it may as well may be demanded, why did God let man fall into ſin to neceſſitate the Intervention of a Surety? ſurely he could have kept him from it, as he did the preſerved Angels It is enough, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom contrived the way for his own Glory, and <hi>Who ſhall teach him, who is most High.</hi> Here then let it be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Covenant of Works did not exclude the Intervening of a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> to take up the matter between God and the Sinner. It is true, it did not make mention of ſuch a thing; nor was it then meet to tell man, that if he ſhould undo himſelf, he ſhould be repaired by another: that was not an <hi>Article</hi> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170983:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> to a Covenant of Works; but it was reſerved for another Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Grace. But there was no obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acle there, or proviſion againſt it; for indeed that Covenant was one of the <hi>Media</hi> for the Illuſtration of the Glory <hi>of Grace,</hi> and therefore it could not in Wiſdom be made obſtructive to it. God is the beſt Interp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eter of his own mind, and he hath thus expounded it, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing that he hath ordained his Son to be the <hi>Repairer of the Breach, and to Redeem us from the Law, Gal.</hi> 4. 4, 5. That when the Law could not Save us, he ſhould, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3. and by making of ſo many precious P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omiſes to all that believe in his Son, of Pardon, Peace, Salvation; of delivering them from the Curſe of the Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God therefore purpoſed this when he gave the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt Covenant, though he did not reveal it till after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet the Covenant of Works poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and inexora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly requires <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for all the breaches made upon it. It will have Reparation for all damages, and Thunders Curſes upon all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Tranſgreſſors of it in any one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10. and God, whoſe honour ſtands engaged to it, to ſee that there
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170983:51"/> be no injury offered to it, will take care that it ſhall be anſwered to the leaſt punct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 18. This Law being at firſt given for a Rule of <hi>Relative Justice,</hi> muſt be exactly kept to: ſo that there is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to be expected.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence without the coming in and undertaking of a ſufficient Surety, there can be no diſcharge to man who is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Delinquent.</hi> The Scripture tells us that the Sinner is <hi>Guilty:</hi> that he is <hi>bound faſt;</hi> that he is <hi>concluded, or ſhut up under Sin.</hi> The word that is Tranſlated, is <hi>in danger,</hi> Mat. 5. 21. Signines, <hi>is held faſt.</hi> It is a <hi>Metaphor</hi> from a condemned man, who is manacled or fettered againſt the day ſet for his Execution. Now the Law ſets no ſuch at liberty, but by an exchange. If it remove the Curſe by taking it off from the Sinner, ſome other muſt become a Curſe in his room, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 12. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> and it muſt be one that is ſufficient; one that can and will make reparation for that Sin; otherwiſe the Sin is not legally puniſhed.</p>
            <p>3. That none but the perſon of the Son of God could be a ſuitable and ſufficient Surety for ſinning man. This will beſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if we conſider, what was requiſite in ſuch a Surety, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170983:52"/> 1 He muſt be one that might be both God and Man in One Perſon. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this Suretiſhip, having a reference to the Law of the firſt Covenant, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he muſt be Man, becauſe it was <hi>Man that had ſinned, Heb.</hi> 2 14. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the work to be done in this ſtate of Suretiſhip, made it neceſſary that he ſhould be God, as will appear in the following Conſiderations. Now, though the reaſon why this beſt ſuited the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon in the Trinity, rather than any other, be abſtruſe to us, yet in the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of theſe affairs, it better became the Son than any of the other perſons. It was meet that the Father ſhould appoint the perſon, and that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould finiſh this Affair, which is done in <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> but <hi>Redemption,</hi> which muſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, beſt ſuited the Order of perſonality, to be the Province of the Second Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He muſt be one whoſe Obedience muſt be of equivalent worth to that of all thoſe for whom he became a Surety, and whatever may be pleaded in point of <hi>Active Obedience,</hi> that that of a meer man might anſwer the Covenant; for the Firſt <hi>Adams</hi> would have done, if he had ſtood, who was but a meer man: yet as to <hi>Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> or Suffering, <hi>Adam</hi> could not expiate his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170983:52"/> own Guilt by ſuffering, much leſs that of his poſterity, who are every one of them become guilty. It could not be any leſs a perſonage that might engage on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count than the Son of God, the Law elſe could not have been ſatisfied, but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence muſt have been done to Relative Juſtice, if the Debtor be diſcharged before all his Debts are paid. He muſt be one that could put an <hi>Infinite merit</hi> into his Obedience, who could do this: and who but the Son of God had this ability?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence he muſt be one able to bear and not ſink under the weight of all the wrath which man had pulled down upon himſelf by his Sin. Now this was <hi>Infinite Wrath,</hi> and therefore the power that was requiſite for the ſuſtaining of it, muſt needs exceed that of a meer Creature. This was the Glory of his Redemption, that the Work was laid upon one who was <hi>mighty to Save,</hi> Iſa. 63. 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 19. If he had broken under it, the deſign had ſurely miſcarried, and the Salvation of Fallen Man had ſtill been left an hopeleſs thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He muſt be one whom God the Father could accept of, and take content in. None could force a Surety upon him; no Law tied him to accept of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170983:53"/> it was his meer pleaſure to do it: had he refuſed it from one that was never ſo ſufficient, it had been no Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Needs therefore muſt it be one in whom he could confide, whom he could truſt, and devolve this work upon: and ſuch only was his own Son. There was none found in <hi>Heaven or Earth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; but of him he gave that Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Math. 3. 17.</p>
            <p n="5">5 He muſt be one who bare us good will, and took delight in the work of Redemption. It was certainly a very great Love to Mankind that could move him to engage in ſuch an Undertaking as this; to expoſe himſelf to ſo ſore a <hi>Travail of Soul,</hi> and ſubmit to undergo ſuch grievous things as it was requiſite for him to do in the making of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Juſtice of God, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the demands of the Law, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere was none but the Son of God that encertained ſuch a reſpect for poor man in his miſery: but he did, <hi>Prov..</hi> 8. 31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ezek. 26. 5.</p>
            <p>4. That the Son of God could not become actually engaged to be mans Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo as that our Redemption ſhould be ſecured by it, but only by a Covenant:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170983:53"/> and this will be manifeſt in the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was abſolately free for the Son of God to chuſe whether he would be a Redeemer, and Surety, or no. The Son of God is a Divine Perſon, and hath all perſonal properties belonging to him: Now one thing proper to a Perſon is, to be <hi>Intelligent,</hi> and by conſequence to have a <hi>power of Election.</hi> Chriſt was no Surety by nature; it was none of his either Eſſential or Perſonal Properties: and he could not be ſo by Coaction, for he is the <hi>Eternal Jehovah,</hi> and therefore cannot be compelled. The Apoſtle plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſerts his full liberty in this matter in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2 God the Father was not abſolutely bound to accept any ſatisfaction at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hands of a ſurety. Had the Son offered it, yet his Suretiſhip could not have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> authentick, but by the intervention of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fathers voluntary conſent. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaid, and reſolved, that fallen man ſhould bear his own puniſhment, and there ſhould be no ſubſtitute accepted in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> room, who ſhould have oppoſed him? he had Juſtice on his ſide; man wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſinner, yea and he did ſo ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> and therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170983:54"/> they are all of them <hi>reſerved in everlaſting Chains.</hi> The caſe was criminal, and an exchange of an offender for an innocent perſon to ſuffer in his room, is ſcarcely allowable among men, to be ſure, the Judge may righteouſly refuſe it. Nor did it flow from Gods natural love to mankind; for he had as much for the Angelical nature, and for the reſidue of men who were not included in this Covenant: it muſt then be of his free choice.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Hence it follows, that neither could the work be ſure to be done, nor the reward of the work be certain to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but upon mutual compact or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement. There could have been no ſecurity on any hand without it; and therefore without this it could not have been a certain truth from eternity, that the Son of God ſhould, in fulneſs of time, come into the world, and become a Saviour; the contrary to which the Scripture aſſures us. Now to ſum up all that hath been ſaid on this account; the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this <hi>Covenant</hi> lies in theſe few following Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That mankind ſtands under a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works, which requires Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170983:54"/> of him, and threatens diſobedience with death. This Covenant being made with <hi>Adam,</hi> as the head of mankind, it included all his poſterity, who were to ſtand or fall with him, in the firſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of his Obedience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Divine Juſtice ſtands enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to this Covenant to ſee it rigorouſly performed according to the true intent of it. Hereby was man reduced to that exigency, that in caſe of Diſobedience, he muſt unavoidably dy, either in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or in his ſurety, Juſtice, lying in the way, muſt be ſatisfied, if mercy appear.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That man is fallen under, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by became forfeited to the law, and liable to the execution of the ſentence of it. It was not his <hi>Original ſtate,</hi> but his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy</hi> that reduced him to this exigency: but by reaſon of that, Divine Juſtice hath him in chaſe, and is purſuing him to Death.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That God will ſave a reſidue of that company, and <hi>deliver them from the wrath to come.</hi> For, if God had purpoſed in himſelf to have deſtroyed all mankind, and to make his wrath known in their perſonal eternal ſufferings, there could have been no neceſſity for a Covenant of Redemption. Juſtice had its full ſcope
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170983:55"/> to take place, upon man, being expoſed unto it by ſin; but mercy had that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its way which left it no room for the exerting of it ſelf without ſuch a Tranſaction</p>
            <p n="5">5. That for this end he will provide a Redeemer for men. He will lay in to make this Salvation ſure, and open a way wherein he may not deny himſelf, but <hi>be both Juſt, and the Juſtifier of all thoſe that believe in his Son:</hi> and that, when mans caſe ſhall call for it; when his miſery ſhall ſtand in need of ſuch a courſe to be taken for its ſuccour, the remedy may not be to ſeek: In all theſe reſpects it was neceſſary, and that becauſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Without a Redeemer <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> could not have met in agreement in the ſalvation of fallen man, either there muſt have been a Claſhing between theſe two <hi>Attributes,</hi> or elſe man muſt have been for ever under the wrath of God. If there had been no Redeemer, there could have been no ſalvation according to the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the diſpenſation of the firſt Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Futurition</hi> of a Redeemer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended abſolutely on this Covenant. Here it had its foundation and riſe, as hath
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170983:55"/> been already proved. Thoſe promiſes, compacts, and engagements between God the Father and God the Son, gave the fututition to Chriſts coming into the World, doing the work of Redemption, and receiving all the Rewards conſequent upon it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If this Redeemer had not come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, and performed the work of mans Redemption, then</p>
            <p n="1">1. Man had continued for ever in a ſtate of Condemnation. He had remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame condition with Fallen Angels, an hopeleſs, forlorn, miſerable Creature. If Chriſt had not died, we had been <hi>without any Hope,</hi> for it is by his Death that we are delivered, Rom. 8. 14. But for this, the Condemnation which fell upon us for ſin, muſt needs have remained irreverſible, and we muſt all have periſhed indubirably.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Grace had been without its declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Glory. That Attribute, which he had a deſign ſignally to advance, and to make himſelf known in and by, to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Admiration, had miſt of this Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and never been thus ſpoken of. <hi>Socinians</hi> indeed labour to perſwade us, that the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of Chriſt for Sin, deſtroys the notion of Grace appearing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170983:56"/> in the Salvation of Sinners, and denies the freedom of his mercy in his ſaving of them; and therefore they will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no ſuch <hi>Satisfaction.</hi> But it is a very great miſtake, for this is the very thing which enhaunceth this Grace of God, and puts a great many wonders into the Declaration of it; for though it is not to be denied, that for God to have ordained that ſinful man ſhould, upon the Confeſſion of his Sins, and voluntary ſubmitting of himſelf to Gods Soveraignty, have received a free pardon of all his ſins, would have been a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous declaration of free Grace, and ſo a wonderful condeſcendency in God, thus to have paſt by the high affronts which are by mans ſin offered to his glorious Name; yet, to conſider, that when man was become ſo involved or intangled by a righteous, and yet a rigorous Law, as that there was no poſſibility of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved without the Death of a Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for him; and that no leſs a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage would ſerve for this than the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Son of God; that the Father ſhould voluntarily ſpare him out of his own boſome, yea and freely appoint him to this Office, that he ſhould by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Law, yea doing and dying
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170983:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> in our nature and ſtead, become a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour for us, that ſo we might not die but live, and mercy might flow down to us, through his being made a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for us, and ſuffering the whole weight of Gods wrath on our account; this makes <hi>Grace</hi> to be the more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly reſplendent, yea, and raiſeth it up to the higheſt pitch of admiration that can be imagined.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 11. <hi>Of the Influence that the Covenant of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption hath into the Covenant of Grace, which is made with us.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Foundation of Fallen Mans Salvation is laid in the Covenant <hi>of Redemption:</hi> here was the price pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to buy him out of the hands of Revenging Juſtice, and purchaſe for him the Eternal Inheritance. Here alſo was ſecurity given that all thoſe for whom it was provided ſhould be made happy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170983:57"/> in the benefit of it. But ſtill there is ſomething wanting in order to the bringing of them into the actual enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this <hi>Title,</hi> and having this Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity made over unto them, and for this the Scripture points us to another <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> diſtinct from this, which is by ſome called the <hi>Covenant of Reoenciliation;</hi> but is more generally known by the name of the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> Not as if the former were not of meer Grace; but here, the Grace which was laid up in the former, breaks forth and is applied effectually unto them, who were before the heirs of it. Nor can theſe Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants be confounded, without greatly darkning the knowledge of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the Love of God to men. Theſe Covenants are Eſſentially diverſe one from the other, having neither the ſame <hi>Parties,</hi> nor the ſame <hi>Articles</hi> in them. In the former the Father and the Son are the parties, in this latter, God and Man. In the former, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God was to be ſatisfied; in the latter, the Grace of God, which was ſo made way for, is to be applied. In the former, the <hi>Law</hi> was to be fulfilled by Chriſt; in the latter the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is to be complied with by man. In the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170983:57"/> former, Chriſt was made one party; in the latter he ſtands as the <hi>Mediator</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both parties, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2. 5. In the former, God Covenanted <hi>for us,</hi> in the latter he Covenants <hi>with us:</hi> there he promiſed us to his Son; here he promiſeth himſelf to us. But though theſe are two Covenants, yet there is a near Conjunction between them, and the latter hath a manifold dependance on the former: yea, ſuch, as all the Believers ſolid comfort, and permanent hope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from it: yea indeed, all the Grace that there is in this Covenant derives from that, as a ſtream from a Fountain; and this may be obſerved more eſpecially in five reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Covenant between God the Father and God the Son, was that which opened the way for his Covenanting with his people. Had not that Covenant been firſt made, this would never have been heard of. The Covenant which God Indents with his people is wholly of Grace, in all the parts of it, as it is made by him: from the foundation to the top-ſtone of it, there is no other voice to be heard but that of Grace. Now, had there not been an <hi>Antecedent Covenant,</hi> which man had ſome relation
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170983:58"/> unto, this might immediately; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any previous prepication have entred into. Grace is free, elſe it were not Grace; and God might have expreſt it to whom he ſaw meet. But when we conſider how it was with man when this Covenant was declared; <hi>viz.</hi> that he ſtood under an Old Covenant of Works, and was related to it as a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor; the <hi>Precept</hi> of it being violated by him, and the <hi>Curſe</hi> of it having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken place on him, and the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God ſtanding obliged to the fulfilling of the <hi>Articles</hi> in that Covenant which God had engaged in; it ſtood up as an high <hi>Wall of Separation between God and Man,</hi> and called for vengeance to be executed upon him according to his Earnings; nor could it be appeaſed without full ſatisfaction given to it for the Injuries done it by the ſinning Creature. All mankind ſtood thus Condemned, and Men of Death. Hence it was neceſſary, that without a <hi>Covenant of Reparation</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing, there could not be a <hi>Covenant of Salvation.</hi> Had not this great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action paſt, the Covenant of Works muſt of neceſſity have taken place, and we muſt have been judged and condemned, and for ever deſtroyed by it. <hi>God muſt</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170983:58"/> 
               <hi>be Just, in being gracious:</hi> he muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>himſelf</hi> or any of his <hi>Attributes: Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth must correſpond;</hi> and how could that be as the caſe ſtood, had there not been ſuch a tranſaction as this? If Juſtice had not interpoſed, Grace might have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded without any more ado; but becauſe <hi>God must be Juſt in Juſtifying a ſinner,</hi> there muſt be proviſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion made that he may be ſo: So that this Covenant of Redemption may be looked upon as the <hi>procuring cauſe</hi> of the Covenant of Grace: it opened the door to it, removed the obſtructions that would elſe have impeded it, and made the way for God to be gracious to poor ſinning man, and ſave him, without any injury done to his juſtice, or violence offered to his law. Here it was that all was laid in that needed to ſatisfy that to the utmoſt farthing: and when that is once appeaſed and its mouth ſtopt, ſo that it hath no more to ſay, Grace hath now its full and free ſcope. In this regard we ſhall find, the Apoſtle redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of our Salvation to this Covenant which was made with Chriſt before time, as the Root and Original of it. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Application of the Grace of the <hi>Covenant of Reconciliation,</hi> whereby any of the children of men are brought into
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170983:59"/> that Covenant, and truly entituled to all the good which is therein promiſed to the Children of God, bears an entire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Covenant of Redemption. That all the Children of men are not taken into the New and Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venant, is certain. That all thoſe to whom it is offered in the Goſpel, do not cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally embrace it, is alſo evident upon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. So that the reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference cannot be becauſe ſome do hear of it, and others do not. That any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to come into this Covenant, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in their unbelief, when they are outwardly called, is their own fault, and it will be charged upon their <hi>wilfulneſs,</hi> Joh. 5. 40. But that any do entertain it, and actually cloſe in with the terms of it, and believe in Chriſt for ſalvation, <hi>is not of themſelves</hi> or by any power of their own, <hi>but of God,</hi> Eph. 2. 8 And if he ſhould have done no more towards their believing, than he did to the other, they would have been for ever under their unbelief. Now there muſt be ſome reaſon aſſigned why God applies it to this and not to the other. This cannot be in the Creature, becauſe all are alike <hi>Children of wrath,</hi> and equally guilty and filthy in their natural ſtate as born, Eph.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170983:59"/> 2. 3. It muſt then be in God. And as the Covenant of Redemption was a reſult of his meer good pleaſure, ſo the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Grace of the New-Covenant, is an act, of his faithfulneſs to his promiſe to Chriſt in that Covenant. Hence, when God comes with his Converting Grace, to beſtow it upon any; when he powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwades the man to <hi>receive the word of truth,</hi> and accept of Jeſus Chriſt upon his offer and terms; and paſſeth by that other who ſits by him, and leaves him to deſpiſe, and make light of the Grace exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to him; he evermore hath his eye upon, and proceeds according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Covenant. So that thoſe who were Covenanted for by Chriſt, and given him of his Father, are brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Covenant of Grace by the Holy Ghoſt. The Spirit of God, when he comes to make the Goſpel Efficacious unto the ſalvation of ſinners, by putting them into the Covenant of Grace, he takes his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures by this Covenant: <hi>he reads thoſe ancient records,</hi> obſerves who they were by <hi>name,</hi> that were given to the Son of God in that tranſaction; he addreſſeth theſe with his power, and cauſeth them <hi>to hear his voice</hi> that they may live; we have ſuch an expreſſion in <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 48. <hi>as many as</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170983:60"/> 
               <hi>were ordained to Eternal life believed.</hi> Yea and our Saviour Chriſt lays that down as a Rule which never fails, <hi>John</hi> 6. 37. <hi>All that the Father giveth me, ſhall come unto me.</hi> Chriſt firſt redeems them by <hi>Price,</hi> and then the ſpirit delivers them by <hi>Power:</hi> he firſt buys them out of the hands of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> and then the Holy Ghoſt comes and fetcheth them out of the <hi>Priſon of Sin,</hi> and from under the <hi>Power of Satan,</hi> and enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them. So that the Covenant of Grace in reſpect to the extenſiveneſs of it, to the Subject, is made juſt as large as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Redemption, that being the pattern according to which it is made, and the reaſon of this is grounded in the former conſideration: for till men are bought out of the hands of the Law they are not free to be indented with in a way of Grace they are not <hi>Sui Juris,</hi> they cannot Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for themſelves; they are the <hi>ſervants of ſin and ſatan,</hi> and priſoners of the Law: except therefore Chriſt have paid the price for them, they are in no capacity for this Grace, but muſt abide under their former ſtate of Condemnation.</p>
            <p n="3">3 All the encouragement which an awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened ſinner hath to embrace &amp; take hold of the Grace which is exhibited in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170983:60"/> Covenant, ariſeth, or is fetched from the Covenant of Redemption. There is a previous <hi>Conviction</hi> which is wont to be wrought in the heart or conſcience of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in order to the propoſal of the Terms of the Goſpel to him: and this is requiſite, for without this <hi>Conviction</hi> he cannot be brought to ſee any need that he ſtands in of the benefits of the New-Covenant; and conſequently cannot be perſwaded to give them entertainment. Now in the working of this <hi>Conviction,</hi> he is made to ſee and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his forlorn wretched ſtate, and how he came to fall into it: that an holy law hath been broken by him; that by vertue hereof he lies under guilt, and is faſt bound by a Sentence of Condemnation, to ſuffer the wrath of God, and vengeance of hell: that he hath to do with a God who is a juſt and a righteous Judge, who will ſtand to his word, and is unchangeable, and will give accompliſhment to all that he hath ſaid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fail. So that when he is under the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of theſe Convictions, and now the Grace of God is tendered him in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and he is ſpoken to, and treated with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the things of his peace: he is told that God is Gracious, ready to pardon, willing to receive him into favour, and to beſtow ſalvation upon him; although theſe thing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170983:61"/> are glad tidings in themſelves, yet there will ariſe demurs and enquiries in him about the matter, and he will be ready to ſay, <hi>how can theſe things be?</hi> he will preſently demand, how then ſhall the Juſtice of God be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for me? how ſhall the mouth of the law be ſtopt? how ſhall the firſt Covenant be fully anſwered and ſtand inviolable? nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be ſuppoſed, that ſuch an one can believingly caſt himſelf upon the Goſpel Grace, and place his reliance upon Chriſt, till he be well ſatisfied upon this account. That is not to be accounted for a true <hi>faith</hi> which raſhly adventures upon accepting of tendred mercy, and never conſiders how it comes, or in what way his ſin may be ſo pardoned, as that God may ſalve the honour of his Juſtice in the Applying of Juſtification unto him. Now this diſcovery is to be made in the Contemplation of the <hi>Covenant of Redemption:</hi> here alone it is that this is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen: for in that it was that this provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was made: Here is the great diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Suretyſhip of Chriſt, in which he put himſelf in the ſinners room and undertook to ſatisfie for him, and God accepted of him in that Relation; and accordingly all that he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the work of his Humiliation was on this ſcore, and in the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170983:61"/> of this Undertaking of his, and ſo it was done on the account of <hi>us Sinners</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 21. Nor indeed could all that Chriſt actually did and ſuſtered give us a through ſatisfaction on this account, without our being able to refer it to this Covenant, in which it is that we come to know what is the Efficacy and Acceptableneſs of it. We cannot then enter into the Covenant of Grace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having an eye on the Covenant of Redemption: <hi>for in the exerting of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Faith, we do not only believe that we ſhall be Saved, but we believe in Chriſt for Salvation, to come to us from his merit, by the application of the vertue of his active and paſſive Obedience to us for our Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: and the acceptance of our perſons and duties in him, being Sprinkled with his Blood:</hi> and all this is a proper reſult from the Covenant we are now treating of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A true Believer, who is entred into the Covenant of Grace with God, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtrongly plead for any Covenant-mercy at his hands without running up hither. It is true, the Covenant of Grace is ſure: it hath its firm and inviolable promiſes belonging to it, and every one that hath entertained it by a true and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170983:62"/> living Faith, is under the promiſes of it, and hath ſuch a Title to them as can never fail him. But let us obſerve, The Covenant of Grace hath its <hi>Conditions;</hi> and it is certain upon daily experience, that the beſt Believers do but poorly on their part perform that which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them, and are often failing in, and falling ſhort of their Duty in this regard: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore they muſt always fix their eye upon that, and look no farther than themſelves, they would not ſeldom, be driven off from Prayer, and loſe their active hopes of acceptance with God; eſpecially when they are over ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with groſs prevarications, and woful ſcandalous failures in their Covenant Obligations: and theſe things have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times held them under doubts, and fears, and darkneſs: and where ſhall they have their Souls lifted up again, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to go to God for the Grace and help which they need, but by remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the Covenant made with Chriſt, in which they are given to him, and undertaken for by him? and not only ſo, but it is to be remembred, that there is no <hi>Meritorious</hi> vertue in the beſt Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or Covenant keeping which they over attain unto, to impetrate any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170983:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> at the hands of God for them. Their <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> when it is beſt, is but <hi>ragged and defiled.</hi> There is ſomething in all they do which wants a pardon, or elſe it cannot be accepted of them; and all the right that we have in any of that good which is laid up in the Promiſes of the Covenant of Grace, is derived to us from the merit of Chriſts Obedience and Satisfaction; and we can believing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ask for it upon no other ſcore. When therefore <hi>David</hi> pleads with God for <hi>good,</hi> he begs of him to be his <hi>Surety, Pſal.</hi> 119. 122. All the Encouragement that a Child of God hath to be impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate with God, and wait on him with expectation to be made to partake in his favours, which derive through the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, is in this, that he knows, or is made to have an active hope, that his name is written in the Covenant of Redemption; and therefore he may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ask it for Chriſts ſake; becauſe he hath both purchaſed this good at the hands of God, and alſo that he did it for him in particular.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is the Covenant of Redemption that eſtabliſheth, or maketh unchangeable, all the mercies and promiſes of the Covenant of Grace. For; although it is ſo that God,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170983:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> who is one party in the Covenant he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, and cannot falſify his word which he hath paſt; yet we who are on the other party, are mutable, and conſequent ly might violate the condition, and ſo come under a forfeiture, and loſe the Promiſes: and therefore ſuch as look no farther than the Covenant of Grace, and conſider the conditions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and the threatnings annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it, ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. 38. <hi>&amp; the like,</hi> have been ready to deny the Doctrine of <hi>Perſeverance;</hi> and ſet up the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable Doctrine of total and final <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staſy,</hi> whereas this Covenant affords us a compleat <hi>Salvo</hi> for all this, becauſe in it, there is a ſecurity provided for the people of God, and a promiſe made to the Son that none of thoſe whom his father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him ſhall be loſt, or be ſuffered to draw back to perdition. The <hi>mercies</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace are <hi>ſure mercies,</hi> becauſe they are the mercies of <hi>David, Iſa.</hi> 55. 3. <hi>i. e.</hi> They are ſuch as were promiſed to him; <hi>viz.</hi> to Chriſt, of whom <hi>David was a Type.</hi> The promiſes indeed are invaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but if it be enquired how they came to be ſo, it is to be obſerved that they are ſaid to be <hi>in him,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 20. It is he who gives them their confirmation: on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is that when God ſpeaks of his
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170983:63"/> continuing his mercy to his people, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their falls and falſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in his Covenant, he Comemorates another Covenant as the ground of his ſo doing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 33, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Not the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which was made with <hi>Davids</hi> Children, which intends the Covenant of Grace, but that which was plighted with <hi>David</hi> himſelf, <hi>i. e.</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that is the Covenant of Redemption. Emblematical of this are theſe obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Scriptures, 1 Kings 15. 3, 4, 5. 2 King. 8. 16. 34. and a clear diſtinction is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made between theſe two Covenants in that memorable place, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 60. There is the <hi>Covenant made with them in the days of their youth, i. e.</hi> in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, which was a Covenant of Grace, under Ceremonies, Signs and Types: this God ſaith he <hi>will Remember, i. e.</hi> graciouſly; he will perform the good for them which was held forth in it, notwithſtanding all they had done to provoke him to the contrary. But how will he do this? he will <hi>eſtabliſh unto them an Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> i. e. the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption: and therefore obſerve, he doth not ſay he will eſtabliſh it <hi>with them;</hi> but <hi>unto them;</hi> i. e. he would make them receive the application
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170983:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> of all the good which was provided for them in it: yea, indeed, this is it which ſets God on work, to bring about the mercy intended for his Choſen, when they are doing all they can to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and lay the greateſt blocks in the way to it; becauſe he hath enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do this in the Eternal Tranſac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on that paſt between him and his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> about it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170983:64"/>
            <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>The A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>tion of this Truth by way of Information.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Doctrine of the Covenant of Redemption is not meerly <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> but exceeding <hi>practical</hi> and it will not be amiſs, to ſubjoin ſome brief improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it, and here;</p>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>USE I.</head>
               <p>May be by way of <hi>Information:</hi> there are ſeveral inferences which may be drawn from and confirmed by it: let a few be here taken notice of:</p>
               <div n="1" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE I.</head>
                  <p>We may here ſee the ground of the certainty, and infallibility of the Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Salvation of all Gods Elect. The
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170983:65"/> right conception and conſideration of this Covenant, will take away all doubts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and afford many undeniable evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of it; and in particular.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We may ſtrongly argue from the inexpreſſible love of God, which herein diſcovers it ſelf abundantly. The ſame love which gave Chriſt for us in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time, provided him for us in the days of Eternity; and that is ſet forth as incomparable, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 16. <hi>God ſo loved,</hi> &amp;c: there is no <hi>reddition.</hi> Nay here is the <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of it; he not only gave him for us when we needed him, but he provided him for us before we needed him: that he made ſure of this ſalvation for us <hi>before all ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> This Covenant was the Lords own <hi>Doing</hi> every way, and may well be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous <hi>in our eyes.</hi> He firſt thought of it, when there was none to put him in mind of it in his Infinite Wiſdom; and he In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented it: and ſure he would never have done all this if his heart had not been ſet upon the Salvation of his Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. It was he who propounded, and ratified this Covenant with his own Son, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 3. and would he have made it, and ſo ratified it, with ſuch firm and inviolable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngagements, if he had not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170983:65"/> been fully reſolved upon the unfailing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of it?</p>
                  <p n="2">2 This will be farther pleaded: becauſe the <hi>Individual names</hi> of thoſe who were thus to be redeemed by Chriſt, were put into the <hi>Articles</hi> of this Covenant. There was not only an agreement made, that there ſhould be a Common price paid, a Common ſtock laid in, which might be ſufficient for as many as would make improvement of it; It might then have been uncertain whether any at all ſhould have been ſaved by it: but the very perſons were covenanted for; and this is evidently intended by the <hi>writing of their names in the Book of life,</hi> of which mention is made in the Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13 8. 17. 8. Which is nothing elſe but the book of the Covenant of Redemption, in which proviſion was made for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of dead ſinners to life again by Jeſus Chriſt, it is therefore called the <hi>Lambs book,</hi> becauſe theſe were given to him to redeem. And <hi>Names</hi> muſt needs indigitate perſons: ſo that the individuals were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented for, and this is a book which hath no blots in it: thoſe that are here written muſt needs be ſaved: what ſaith Chriſt himſelf about it? <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 37. <hi>All that the Father hath given me ſhall come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170983:66"/> 3. All theſe are firmly promiſed and engaged to Chriſt in this Covenant, they ſhall be his Seed, upon the performance of the Articles that were propoſed unto him. This was one Encouragement that his Father offered to him, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. 10 Pſal. 22. 30. and how do they come to be the Seed of Chriſt, and conſequently the Children of God, but by being brought into the Covenant of Grace, and under the Promiſe of Eternal Life, Gal. 3. 26. Now this was the Word and Promiſe of God himſelf; The <hi>Unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> God, the God that <hi>cannot Lie:</hi> and it is made to his own Son; and upon it he undertook the work, and went through it, in expectation of the compleat Accompliſhment of it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>for the Joy that was ſet before him, &amp;c.</hi> and what can we poſſibly conceive to be more firm?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Sufficiency of the Redeemer muſt needs make this Salvation ſure to thoſe for whom it was provided. In this Covenant God took care to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide one who was every way able to do the work which he was to Engage in; and therefore it was utterly impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that it ſhould fail in his hands. For this reaſon he is ſaid to be a <hi>strong Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170983:66"/> Jer. 50. 34. and <hi>Mighty to ſave,</hi> Iſa. 63. 1. ſee alſo for this, Deut. 33. 23 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. 19. He is able to bear down all Oppoſition that can be made againſt him and there is no adverſe power that can ſo interpoſe as to obſtruct this Salvation, but it is carried on with a ſtrong hand: needs then muſt it be without fail brought about.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 By this Covenant, that which lay in the way as the great Obſtacle or hindrance of mans Salvation, is altogether removed, ſo as it ſhall no longer impede it: <hi>viz. the justice of the firſt Covenant.</hi> Fallen man is by a Righteous Law condemned, and Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice demands the life of the ſinner for its ſatisfaction: but <hi>in the Covenant of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Juſtice it ſelf is not only pacified, but ſtands as deeply engaged for the Salvation of Gods Redeemed, as any other of the Divine Attributes:</hi> it is in Combination with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in this buſineſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85. 10. and by vertue of this tranſaction, not only Grace and Mercy, but Juſtice alſo appears glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and triumphantly in the ſinners de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, 1 Joh. 1. 9. and what is there then that ſhould impede this buſineſs? Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes here breaks forth with Luſtre, and God no way wrongs either his Truth or his Holineſs, in ſaving the chief of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170983:67"/> ſinners by Jeſus Chriſt. For the Son of God becoming a ſurety for miſerable man, who was by the fall undone, and became inſolvent to the <hi>Law,</hi> he diſchargeth him of all his Obligations to that Covenant; &amp; having given compleat ſatisfaction to it in all its demands, the ſinner is, <hi>by the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Act of Juſtice,</hi> diſcharged of that debt: and now God declares his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in Juſtifying of him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 26. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Apoſtle makes a Challenge, he ſtrengthens it by forming ſuch an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 34. <hi>Who is he that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth? It is Chriſt that Dyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Hence if any of Gods Elect ſhould fail of being brought into the Covenant of Grace, and ſo being ſaved; this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant would ſo far be defeated and made void. For, if the Covenant were ſo made as that the Names of thoſe who were to be Redeemed, were all put into it, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all theſe muſt be brought into the poſſeſſion of the good Provided for them or elſe there muſt be ſome of thoſe loſt whom the Father had given to Chriſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which he himſelf declares, and it would certainly tend greatly to his Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Thoſe then who have attained to be able to read their names written in the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170983:67"/> book of <hi>Liſe,</hi> and have ſo <hi>made their Flecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure,</hi> may hereby be aſſured, of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſtanding in this Covenant, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themſelves in the confident expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the unfailing aſſiſtance of the Grace of God, to Preſerve them unto Life Eternal, according to <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 6.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE II.</head>
                  <p>Here we ſee where and whence thoſe <hi>Abſolute promiſes</hi> Recorded in the Scripture, have their Originall. There is a great diſpute in the world about <hi>Abſolute Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> The <hi>Arminians,</hi> do wholly deny any ſuch to be at all. The <hi>Antinomians</hi> do err as much on the other hand in aſſerting them to be made to <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as ſinners.</hi> A right underſtanding of this Covenant, and the true rela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion which theſe promiſes have to it, will give us light for the clearing of all theſe doubts. Here then take theſe following Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That there are no promiſes of Gods ſpecial favour Recorded in His Word, but what do belong unto ſome Covenant or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. All Gods dealings with mankind, which refer to their Everlaſting Eſtate, are in the way of a Covenant. As ſoon as God had Created man, he plighted a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170983:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> with him, in which <hi>Life and Death</hi> were ſet before him: and when the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was violated by mans ſin, and he had forfeited the Life that was promiſed, and purchaſed the Death threatned in that God having a deſign of ſaving a number of this unhappy race, made the diſcoveries of an <hi>Hope</hi> to him, by bringing in a New-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, &amp; this was revealed unto man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon his <hi>Apoſtaſy.</hi> This indeed is a way beſt ſuited to the nature of man; and God hath vouchſafed thus to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate himſelf thereunto, ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 3. And elſewhere frequently.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That it is of the nature of a Covenant Promiſe to be joyned with ſome Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This Concluſion follows from the conſideration of a Covenant in General, which is a <hi>Mutual Obligation,</hi> wherein there are two parties engaged each to the other: ſo that the engagement on one part, ſtands related to the engagement on the other part, &amp; thereupon it is <hi>Hypothetical.</hi> A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant Promiſe is a Promiſe which is made with a <hi>relative reſpect</hi> to ſomething that is expected from him to whom it is made, on the performance whereof the <hi>Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Promiſe ſtands and on the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170983:68"/> whereof it becomes void: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is ſometimes expreſſed, always intended, a <hi>Threatning</hi> to take place inſtead of the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> in caſe of ſuch a failure: and a perſon hath no farther hold on the Promiſe, than as he is under the <hi>Condition</hi> of it. So was the promiſe of the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 2. And therefore there was alſo a Threatning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17. Thus alſo is the Goſpel Covenant Promiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and connected, <hi>Mark,</hi> 16, 16.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 That theſe <hi>Abſolute Promiſes</hi> are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>Abſolute,</hi> becauſe they have to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending Condition</hi> in the Covenant of Grace. Hither we are to refer all ſuch Promiſes as do engage the <hi>giving of the conditions of the Covenant of Grace</hi> to theſe or thoſe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch as theſe are to be found in the Book of God, particularly in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 18 <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 25, 26, 27. And ſeveral more of the ſame Tenour.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Promiſes can have no conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depending in the Covenant of Grace, for ſo they would argue a contradiction; for God to ſay, I will <hi>Convert</hi> you, if you will <hi>Convert</hi> yourſelves; I will give <hi>you a New heart,</hi> if you will <hi>make a New Heart to yourſelves;</hi> I will give you <hi>Faith to believe,</hi> if you will <hi>believe</hi> in your own ſtrength. Theſe promiſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170983:69"/> God plainly undertaking, freely and fully to work that in ſinners, which is required in the <hi>Goſpel Covenant,</hi> in order to their being made partakers in the good therein promiſed; and for that reaſon are they ſaid to be <hi>Abſclute,</hi> with reſpect to the Goſpel Covenant, becauſe they bear no reſpect to the Condition which is therein propounded and required ſo as to engage for it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That all theſe promiſes have their <hi>Conditions,</hi> and the performance of them, contained in the Covenant of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hence it is that they are given in the Word of God, to be the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the great Efficacy of that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and to aſſure us of the certain and unfailing fulfilment of it: that no ſin or unworthineſs of the Creature, ſhall be able to obſtruct it, how much ſoever they have done to throw blocks in the way, and to provoke God to reject them, yet it ſhall not prevent the breaking out of his grace in the Accompliſhment thereof; becauſe all that Gods Elect do or can do, to hinder their own Salvati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and bring wrath upon themſelves, is taken care about, and full ſatisfaction is made for it in that Covenant by our
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170983:69"/> Surety: and hereupon do theſe Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions follow.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That thoſe Promiſes are not of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Application. They do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage God to all men univerſally: they are not made to <hi>Sinners as Sinners; i. e.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one can challenge the application of them to themſelves on that account, or for this reaſon, becauſe they are <hi>Sinners.</hi> But they are confined to the <hi>Election of God,</hi> or to thoſe who are comprehended in the Covenant of Redemption; and they only do <hi>obtain them,</hi> Rom. 11. 7. <hi>The Election hath obtained.</hi> It is not for every one that reads theſe Promiſes, to confide and lot upon it, that they are made unto him, and to take them to be the ground of his Faith, and to conclude that by vertue of them, he ſhall be Saved. God only knows whom they belong to, before ſuch time as there is a particular application made of them by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That no man can challenge theſe Promiſes as his own, till he be brought under the Covenant of Grace, and the Conditions of it are wrought in him. Theſe Promiſes do not diſcover any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of <hi>Salvation</hi> unto men, than that which is Revealed in the Goſpel.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170983:70"/> which is by Faith in Chriſt, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto Life: and therefore though theſe promiſes are not annexed to the Goſpel Condition, or depend upon it, yet they do engage for it, <hi>viz. to give a New Heart;</hi> to beſtow Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance upon them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and upon this account, they diſcover themſelves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to this or that man in particular, in the application which the Spirit of God doth make of theſe conditions to him: When therefore the Condition is wrought in the Soul, then the man may and ought to apply them, and take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the comfort of them, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Love of God to him, and his Faithfulneſs to his own purpoſes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which he made to Chriſt in the Eeerlaſting Covenant: but till then we have no aſſurance. Our <hi>Election</hi> is only made ſure, by ſecuring our <hi>Calling,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This notwithſtanding, theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are uſeful to be looked upon by the <hi>Awakened,</hi> though at preſent <hi>Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> Sinner, to Engage him to wait upon, and hope in God for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the work in him, and that notwithſtanding his own ſinful unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and weakneſs: ſince they declare
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170983:70"/> to him, that <hi>Gods Grace is abſolutely inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on any qualifications in the Creature,</hi> and cannot be obſtructed by the abſence of them; and may thereupon direct him whither to go for Grace to believe, and for Sanctification; and whence he muſt derive it, if ever he partake in it. They ſay that God is the Author of all and therefore all the Objections and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements which they are ready to gather from the conditions in that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and their own inability to perform them, are here recovered, by ſhewing them who is the Author of this Grace: and becauſe he hath abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſaid that he will do it for ſome, it gives us hope that if we wait upon him for it, he will do it for us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Yea theſe promiſes ſignify to all where the Goſpel comes, that there is no hindrance <hi>on Gods part,</hi> why he may not come and pardon and heal the ſinner nor any impediment on our part by rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Impenitency, unbelief, or great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, but that he may look over, break through, and for all them come to us, and afford us this Salvation for his own Great Names Sake, and by vertue of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which he hath made with his own
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170983:71"/> Son; and that notwithſtanding all our unworthineſs, and indiſpoſedneſs to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. In a word, theſe Promiſes ſignify that the buſineſs of Redemption is ſecured, and that God hath already taken up, &amp; is ſatisfied in the Suretiſhip of His Son, and accounts himſelf under an inviolable bond to perform the Good promiſed, for all thoſe who were appointed to be the Heirs of this great Salvation: and how much of encouragement is there in this for poor guilty ſinners that have no other hope before them?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE III.</head>
                  <p>Here we ſee upon how ſtrong a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation a believers hopes for Glory are laid. We have obſerved that there is a neer connection between the Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and that of Grace: and here is one principal inference which is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from the connection that he who by Faith in Chriſt is brought into the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, may derive the ſtrength of hope and holy confidence to himſelf from the Ancient Covenant of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; becauſe <hi>his being in this undeniably ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth him to have been included in that:</hi> and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170983:71"/> then, no wonder if his faith be often ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his hopes unſetled, if he do not keep his eye continually upon this. But a right ſpeculation here will wonderfully nouriſh and ſtrengthen him. <hi>Hope</hi> is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers <hi>Anchor,</hi> with which he keeps himſelf from running adrift in hours of Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it is that which he <hi>Lives upon</hi> till he comes to Heaven, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 24. How much then may he ſtrengthen this by ſuch a contemplation? for from this Covenant there flow down to him theſe Glorious diſcoveries.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Here he ſees that <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> is made to the Juſtice of God for his ſins; and that his <hi>happineſs</hi> is bought and paid for. He may here diſcern, not only a <hi>ſufficient</hi> price, but a <hi>Covenant</hi> price laid down; ſuch as was indented for by God himſelf, and therein all his demands anſwered; and therefore it is accepted by him: to that the law hath nothing, as a Covenant, to implead him for; whereby all the charges of ſatan and his own miſgiving heart that are made againſt him are fully confuted: and it no ways daſheth his Hope to reflect and conſider what he hath been in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, (though it humbleth and abaſeth him) conſidering what he now is in Chriſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170983:72"/> Jeſus, <hi>Rom</hi> 8. 1. Here he knows where he hath a right and title to the Glorious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and how it was procured for him: that it is already bought and paid for in his name, and for that reaſon it ſhall aſſuredly be beſtowed upon him in due time.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Here he ſees all the hard conditions of life, which are propounded in the Law, to be fully ſatisfied and performed. The Law ſaith <hi>do this and Live, ie.</hi> do it perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conſtantly, without any failure or defect: though this were fair and eaſy to man in integrity, when he had the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God upon him, yet now he finds it hard, yea an impoſſibility in himſelf to comport with all; &amp; the more he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, the more apprehenſive he is of his ſhort coming: and this makes a legal life to be an horrible ſlavery. But he here is certified that Chriſt became ſurety for all this, and that he hath fully performed thoſe terms to a tittle, and this upon his account; ſo that hereupon he hath brought him to ſtand upon better terms of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 5. and now, his dayly defects, though they grieve him, yet they do not hinder or damp his expectation of the life which is Promiſed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Here alſo he ſees Jeſus Chriſt to be
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170983:72"/> the <hi>undertaker</hi> for all that which is to be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e by him in order to Salvation <hi>i e.</hi> for the performing and accompliſhing of the very Goſpel Covenant. When the law is ſatisfied for our offences, there is yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be <hi>done</hi> by us in order to Salvation The new Covenant requires <hi>Faith, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and Perſeverance:</hi> and as we could not put the Firſt Grace into our ſelves, by converſion, ſo neither can we carry the work on when it is begun, nor withſtand all the powerful Temptations that ly in our way, and be <hi>Faithful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto the Death,</hi> that we may <hi>receive the Crown of Life:</hi> and yet all this muſt be, according to the tenour of the Covenant, and the looking meerly upon this, makes a Child of God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be afraid whether he ſhall hold out, he finds ſo much ſtrength ſet againſt him, and ſo much infirmity attending on him. But here is his <hi>Hope</hi> ſetled; in this Covenant Jeſus Chriſt was the undertaker for this alſo; for he is to <hi>bring</hi> his Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to <hi>Glory Heb,</hi> 2. 10. hence that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Joh</hi> 6. 37. <hi>He gave himſelf for his Church,</hi> not only to <hi>ſatisfy</hi> for them, but alſo to <hi>ſanctify</hi> them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that now he knows whither to go, and where to ask for all the help that he ſtands in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eed of where it cannot be denied him.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170983:73"/> 4 Here he alſo ſees all his Objections ſatisfactorily anſwered, and Doubts reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. When any thing offers to perplex him he brings it hither, and here he finds a full relief againſt it. If the Terrible Aſpect of Gods <hi>Juſtice</hi> Terrifies him, he comes hither and finds it to be ſatisfied, and <hi>kiſſing of Mercy.</hi> If the conſideration of Gods ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Holineſs ſtartles him, he ſees it glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Jeſus Chriſt, and mightily advanced in bringing ſo much Honour to God by this way of Salvation thus laid out. If the thoughts of his Sins Amaze him, and the Terrible Threatinings againſt them become a Terrour to him, here he finds the Curſe exacted, and all his Sins ſatisfied for, and the whole penalty of them born: when his ſins look never ſo great and formidable to him, here he finds, a ſacrifice provided which is of infinite value. If his own <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> aſhame him, by reaſon of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul imperfection of it, and the many blemiſhes that there are upon it, here he diſcovers One that is Perfect and Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid in for him. If his own <hi>Weakneſs</hi> diſcourage him, and he be ready to ſink under the ſenſe of it, here he finds a ſtrength prepared for him, Even an <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Arm underneath</hi> to ſupport him. So that in nothing that can carry any appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170983:73"/> of a Diſcouragement in it, is he at a loſs in this Covenant to find a full relief againſt it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And here he hath ſtrong grounds of Confidence againſt all the Enemies of his Salvation. He need not be afraid of any accuſations they can bring in againſt him, before God, though he knows that there is too much that can be truly ſaid againſt him, by reaſon of his daily ſollies, ſhort comings, aberrations: becauſe he knows that, his name being in the Covenant, that will ſpeak more for him, than all they can do againſt him; and his <hi>Redeemer</hi> at the Right Hand of God is his Advocate, to anſwer all that can be brought in againſt him by way of accuſation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 34. Nor needs he be afraid of their underminings, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible oppoſition, though he knows that they are too ſubtile for him, and a great deal ſtranger than he is; becauſe he is aſſured of this, that his Redeemer is <hi>Strong,</hi> and <hi>Faithful,</hi> and muſt anſwer for him to God, being in that Covenant engaged to bring him to Salvation. And what ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the hopes of ſuch an one? Or who ſhall be able to make him aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of this <hi>Hope?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="inference">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170983:74"/>
                  <head>INFERENCE IV.</head>
                  <p>Here we ſee the True and proper ground or reaſon of the Juſtification of a ſinner. This <hi>Article hath a great deal of Myſtery in it,</hi> and many are loſt in their Speculations about it, for want of a Clue to lead them through i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. But the conſideration of the Covenant of Redemption, will clear this great Truth from all difficulties which men are pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>plexed with about it. <hi>The Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a ſinner,</hi> though as it is conferred upon him in a way of <hi>Imputation,</hi> it is an act of <hi>Rich Grace;</hi> yet in it ſelf it is a <hi>Law act,</hi> and ought to proceed according to Truth and Equity; it is a Scripture Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 15. And the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this oftentimes makes an awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſoul to ſtumble and haeſitate: he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſay, <hi>ſhall not the Judge of the Earth do right:</hi> now I have ſinned, I have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Law, and it can never ceaſe to be a truth, that I have ſo done: how then ſhall God Pronounce me juſt, righteous, acquitted, who am a ſinner. What <hi>Truth</hi> can there be in ſuch a ſentence? for my Faith cannot make the leaſt ſatisfaction for my ſins; and my obedience is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp; if God ſhould be <hi>strict to mark</hi> the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170983:74"/> iniquity mixing with it, <hi>I could not ſtand:</hi> where then is the Righteouſneſs of God, which is ſo much celebrated in Scripture, how doth he ſtand to his own Law, which ſaith that <hi>the ſinner ſhall dy?</hi> Now all theſe ſcruples will come to be fully taken off, and the Soul will be aboundantly ſatisfied in the Contemplation of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. for;</p>
                  <p n="1">1 If faith in Jeſus Chriſt were only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in the Covenant of Grace, for our Juſtification, we could not poſſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> if there were no farther diſcovery made of the reaſon and ground of this. If God had not ſtood in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the firſt Covenant to the terms of it, and his <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in that engagement, it had not been ſo hard to underſtand how he might acquit the ſinner by beſtowing of a Free Pardon upon him, and there would have been no need for us to look any farther than to Grace in it, ſuppoſing it conſiſtent with So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign <hi>Holineſs</hi> thus to have done. But when we remember that there was ſuch a Covenant, and that both Gods <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> were deeply concerned in it, to ſee to the compleat performance of it, and that therfore the breach of it muſt be ſatisfied for, or elſe there can be no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170983:75"/> or acquittance given; how ſhall we take up ſatisfied in ſuch an Offer, until we ſee how or in what way this ſatisfaction can be made? and when we are Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that neither our Faith nor Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can be Meritorious, or anſwer the Demands of the Law, we muſt needs look yet farther?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hence, in the Covenant of Grace, the Obedience of Chriſt is propounded to a ſinner, as the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> which he is to believe in him for. Chriſts Righteouſneſs is exhibited as both the <hi>Meritoorius,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Material</hi> cauſe of our being acquitted before God. To perſwade us to Embrace it, and Caſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſelves upon it, it preſents it before us as a <hi>Perfect Righteouſneſs,</hi> which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way full, and anſwerable to the Law in all points, having enough in it to anſwer all the Demands of that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, hence we read, <hi>Rom:</hi> 5: 18, 19. How compleatly this makes up all that which was procured by <hi>Mans Offence:</hi> but,</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The way how this Righteouſneſs came to be ours by <hi>Imputation,</hi> and ſo accepted for us unto our <hi>Juſtification,</hi> is diſcovered in and by the Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170983:75"/> of the Covenant of Redemption; in which we may Obſerve.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we were there Covenanted for. This Covenant was not made <hi>with</hi> us but <hi>for</hi> us. Though Chriſt were the only <hi>Party</hi> Covenanting with his Father, yet we were the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the Covenant. That great Tranſaction was made with reſpect to us, and in order to the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about of our Salvation: ſo that, as Chriſt was the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> ſo we were the Perſons to be <hi>Redeemed</hi> by Him; <hi>Galatians,</hi> 4: 5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That hence all that Chriſt did in that Great Work, was for us, or upon our account. <hi>He Lived not for Himſelf, neither Dyed He for Himſelf, but for us, Gal.</hi> 2. 20. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Ult.</hi> He had no occaſion to put himſelf into the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Redeemer upon his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: He Owed no Active Obedience to the Law for himſelf, being the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Son of God: nor did he deſerve to ſuffer any Penalty for himſelf, for he <hi>was without ſin;</hi> it was therefore for ſuch as did need all this to be done for them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 4. 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170983:76"/> 3 That what he thus did was upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement between his Father and him. That there firſt paſt a firm Covenant about it, before he engaged actually in the doing of it: ſo that there was a firm Foundation laid for the ſecuring of the Fruit and Benefit of it, and for this reaſon, the Blood of Chriſt is called <hi>the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, Hebr.</hi> 13: 20. Becauſe it was Shed upon this Compact.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That he had a firm and inviolable Promiſe from his Father, that all this ſhould be made ours, and that we ſhould reap the fruit and benefit of it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 10. It was a Promiſe made by God <hi>who cannot lie,</hi> and it was ſealed by <hi>Two Immutable things, Hebr.</hi> 6. 18. There was Gods <hi>Purpoſe</hi> and his <hi>Oath</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. Now when all theſe things are put together, they clear up the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Gods Proceeding: for though it be a ſinner that ſtands at the Bar, and one who is in himſelf by Law a man of Death; yet when it is made to appear that he was redeemed by an Everlaſting Covenant. That <hi>Temporary</hi> Covenant of Works cannot infringe it, but muſt be ſubſervient unto it. And ſince he is Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170983:76"/> in <hi>his ſurety,</hi> how Unrighteous ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is in himſelf, God is Righteous in Juſtifying of him, and no injuſtice can juſtly be charged upon him, in declaring him to be Righteous, by vertue of this Righteouſneſs. So that our Juſtification is built upon a Foundation which is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the Earth or Heavens.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="inference">
                  <head>INFERENCE V.</head>
                  <p>Here we Learn that mans whole Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proceeds from God himſelf, It plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells us how little hand poor man hath in his own deliverance from miſery, and obtaining of bleſſedneſs, and this will be diſcovered in two Propoſitions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That the foundation of mans Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was laid in this Covenant. From hence it is that it derives its riſe and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that any of the undone Children of Adam are brought to Inherit eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they owe the whole acknowledgment of it hither Fallen man could not have bin ſaved without ſuch a Covenant: his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs abſolutely depended upon the good will of God; and theſe are the firſt thoughts that God enterteined in himſelf about mans delivery; and here began
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170983:77"/> the <hi>futurition</hi> of it. If God had not <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen them firſt,</hi> they would never have <hi>Choſen him.</hi> If Chriſt had not come to be a Redeemer, all the children of men muſt have died hopeleſly in their ſins, and if God the Father had not Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted with his Son about his coming on this great errand, he had certainly never come again, if Chriſts obedience had not been <hi>accepted</hi> with God upon the account of thoſe for whom he both Did and Died, it could never have been <hi>Imputed</hi> to them ſo as to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the procuring cauſe of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if God had not thus Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted with his Son about it, it had never been thus <hi>accepted.</hi> No one of theſe things could have been left out, in this great affair. Now all this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from God himſelf, it is his own doing, The creature that is to be ſaved by it, was not there to ſpeak for it ſelf, for it was before the Creation; ſo that neither was there any other Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated being to ſpeak unto God in its behalf. If God had not thought of it and done it, it had never been; for this was an eternal act; it paſt in the Divine Counſel, and was ratified there before the world was.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170983:77"/> II That all that which contributes to mans Salvation, ariſeth and flows down from this Covenant whatſoever elſe can be mentioned or thought of, that hath any influence into the eternal Salvation of the children of men, is hither to be reduced, as to the <hi>Original</hi> of it, Here were the contrivances and ways for the accompliſhment of all this buſineſs laid out, and moſt wiſely delineated: Here was all that was needful to bring ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to the actual poſſeſſion of eternal life prepared: yea the very Covenant of Grace in and by which the Treaty is held and carried on between God and Sinners under the Goſpel Diſpenſation is here fountained. Not only the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> it ſelf, but the <hi>Application</hi> of the Redemption is wholly derived from hence in all the parts and <hi>ſteps</hi> of it: in this Covenant it was that Chriſt was <hi>made all for us,</hi> that he might be ſo to us 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 1. 30. All the Promiſes which were made, of providing the Ordinances for, and giving them to men, of ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the means of Grace and the calls of the Goſpel; of ſending the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit to them, and into them, of drawing ſinners home to Jeſus Chriſt, &amp; making <hi>them</hi> to comply with him on his
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170983:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> terms, of keeping them in him, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them from Falling away from Grace after they are in him; and of bringing them to, and making them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit Eternal Glory at the laſt, they are all the promiſes of this Covenant, and the engaged benefits of Chriſts Undertaking were made to him upon it, and were fulfilled eminently upon his having done the Work, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that all this is of God: becauſe it is all of it laid up in Gods Covenant; yea in ſuch a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant wherein there were none engaged as Parties undertaking, but ſuch Perſons as were God.</p>
                  <p>Hence alſo the Application of this good to us muſt needs be acknowledged to this, and here muſt be aſſigned the reaſon why any of us do <hi>believe that we may be ſaved:</hi> it was not becauſe we were enclined or diſpoſed to it more than others, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Salvation was <hi>Secured</hi> for us in that Covenant, and muſt be in this way <hi>Promoved:</hi> and how may this ſerve <hi>to hide pride from man,</hi> and lead him up to an humble acknowledgment of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all his hopes?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:170983:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CHAPTER XIII. <hi>The Farther Application by Way of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Conſolation.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>USE II.</head>
               <p>For <hi>EXHORTATION,</hi> and <hi>DIRECTION,</hi> to the People of God; and that in Four Reſpects.</p>
               <p>1 LAbour to Clear up and to be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your Intereſt in and Relation to this Covenant. Reſt not Contented till you have gotten ſome good Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that your Names were written in the Book of Life, and to move you hereto, Conſider theſe Two Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a Thing that may be known. Although the Eternal Tranſaction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween GOD the Father, and GOD the Son, be a Secret Hidden from the World, and no Man can have any particular
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170983:79"/> knowledge of it referring to himſelf, till he be made partakers in the ſpecial fruits of it: yet the Believer in regard of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, may obtain a clear acquaintance with it: he may be able to diſcern and read it. There is a way Revealed in the Scripture whereby we may come to know what was contrived about us in the days of Eternity, and be aſſured that Jeſus Chriſt hath paid the full Price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: not only that he hath done ſo for ſome, but for us in particular. Were it not ſo, that Precept in, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10. had been ſuperfluous: yea all the Commands given us to <hi>Prove</hi> and <hi>Try</hi> our own State were vain: For unleſs our Trial Iſſue here we are ſtill left at a loſs. But there is a Promiſe made to the People of God that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, that <hi>He will ſhow them His Covenant, Pſal.</hi> 25. 14. <hi>i. e.</hi> The Great ſecret of the Covenant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, ſhall be diſcovered to them, by making of them to know that God loved them with an Everlaſting Love.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The foundation of all your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation</hi> is laid in this Covenant. All the Comfort of the Children of God reſolves ultimatly into this, that <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170983:79"/> 
                  <hi>Loved us and gave himſelf for us:</hi> but this he did not do for all the world but only for a ſelect company, whom his Father had given unto him, and theſe are they whom he Covenanted for before the world was made. If ever we be ſaved, it muſt be by the vertue and application of the ſatisfaction of Chriſt to us; this is applied to none but thoſe whom he indented for, and was appointed by his Father to Redeem: ſo that if we would know whether our ſins are Pardoned, and Juſtice be atoned to us, it muſt be by knowing that Chriſts death is become ours, and accepted for us: and the way to be ſatisfied in this, is by finding our names <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that roll or liſt, which was entred in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he record: of Heaven before time was: and till we come to underſtand this, how can we be free from the fears and terrors of the wrath to come!</p>
               <p>Now the Scripture way wherein we are directed to arive at this knowledg, is by following of the ſtreams up to the fountain. There are ſome ſtreams of common bounty, which flow from God the Fountain of Goodneſs, to all the World; he being the common Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to all his Creatures; and there are
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170983:80"/> none but do partake more or leſs of his <hi>Benignity,</hi> Pſal. 145. 9. Mat. 5. 45. But yet a man may ſwim in the fulneſs of all theſe favours, yea be glutted with them, and yet be an utter ſtranger to this Covenant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 14. Theſe are kindneſſes which God can allow to his Enemies. But there are other diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing favours, which the great King reſerves to beſtow only on thoſe whom he hath ſet his heart upon, &amp; is reſolved to make them his ſpecial favourites: ſo that whoſoever is made to enjoy any of theſe, he may hereby certainly know that God hath a mind to <hi>honour him,</hi> and intends Eternal Life for him. There are peculiar tokens of the Love of God which he gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es to none but ſuch as have found Grace in his ſight; and thoſe that enjoy them, may from thence unerringly conclude that they were giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to Chriſt in an Everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. We may read the deſcent of theſe in Rom. 8: 29. 30. There is a <hi>white Stone, and a new Name which is not Legible by any but him who hath it.</hi> This God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon none other but thoſe who were thus Covenanted for. There is a powerful work of Converſion wrought in the Soul, by cauſing the man to paſs
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170983:80"/> from death to life, the donation of the Spirit of Adoption by which we are enabled to <hi>Cry, Abba Father,</hi> the infuſion of the Grace of Sanctification, in which there is a wonderful change made, a <hi>New Creature</hi> brought forth, <hi>all old things paſt away, and all things become new</hi> in him. Now theſe are all the gifts of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace, they are the ſecret convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from the Well-head of Electing Love, they are the <hi>Covenant Mercies,</hi> and <hi>things that Accompany Salvation:</hi> if then you are called by his power, ſeized by his Spirit, ſanctified by his Grace; you may by this be aſſured that you were Choſen in Chriſt, and Covenanted for with him. Theſe benefits are not ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered promiſcuouſly, but are given pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly. Labour therefore to have and diſcover ſuch Operations as theſe in your hearts, and to be more and more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the reality of them: this will be the way to derive joy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation from the Fountain, and fetch down comfort into your Souls as far as from Eternity.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Be exhorted to make improvement of your intereſt in this Covenant, for your eſtabliſhment againſt the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations which may aſſault you. We may
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170983:81"/> ſafely determine, that all the ſhakings or unſettlings of a believers ſaith, and all the diſcouragements under which he La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at any time, do ariſe either from a want of his being fortified in this Covenant, or from a neglect of applying and improving it ſeaſonably: For this hath enough in it to diſſolve all doubts, and anſwer all objections, if it be wiſely improved by us: uſe it therefore;</p>
               <p n="1">1 To ſilence all the accuſations which may ariſe from the Covenant of Works. A Believer is ſometimes greatly Puzled, and in a Shock of ſore Temptation he is hurried to the <hi>Old Covenant,</hi> where ſin is declared againſt, and the ſinner is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and Juſtice ſtands engaged to do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution accordingly: and now he is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perplexed to think how the Law and Grace can conſiſt, and ſo how ſuch a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he is can be Saved, and he is ready to ſink under it. Indeed in the Covenant of Grace he hears of pardon and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which are aſſured to the Sinner up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on believing, and that is a precious thing; but he knows not how to reconcile this to what the Law ſaith; that <hi>God is Holy and of purer eyes than to behold Iniquity,</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:170983:81"/> that <hi>Sinners ſhall not ſtand in his ſight;</hi> &amp; ſuch an one hath he notoriouſly been; and how ſhould he make thoſe things to bear? Now Repair to the Covenant of Redemption, and take a through view of it, and there you ſhall find that all this is ſufficiently taken care about, and every difficulty that you can think of, is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether removed. The Covenant of Grace indeed ſpeaks of favour and mercy to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, freely to be beſtowed upon them by God through Chriſt, but in the Covenant of Redemption you may ſee how all this is brought about, and be ſatisfied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it: for in this Covenant there is an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering provided, a compleat Sacrifice la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in: here is the Blood of a Saviour to be ſhed, his precious life to be laid down in exchange for the life of the Sinner, in which there is infinitely more value than in the lives of all the World; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Law require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the hands of the Sinner is here anſwered. Here is Juſtice ſitting in Triumph, Holineſs glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly Exalted, the Law fulfilled to the utmoſt of all that it can demand: here God declares his hatred againſt Sin ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, and all that was demanded in the Covenant of Works, is made good to the utmoſt farthing; and now what
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170983:82"/> ſhould hinder the flowing down of the Grace of the New Covenant to the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Gods Elect, ſince it appears, that <hi>he can be both Juſt and the Justifier of them that believe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 To remove all the doubts that may ariſe in you reſpecting the Covenant, of Grace. In this very Covenant, Satan the adverſary of Gods People ſeeks to find many ſlaws, and thereupon to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter their minds and diſturb their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, ſo as that many times they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with that quietneſs repoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon it, or ſuck that ſweet and comfort out of it, which is therein provided for them: and the uſual ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem which he is wont to entangle them by, is the conſideration that though there are very great and Precious Promiſes held out to the Children of God in that Covenant, enough to ſatisfy their moſt enlarged deſires, if they could appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate them to themſelves; yet in the Goſpel all theſe Promiſes come with conditions annexed to them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are no farther ours than the condition is to be found wrought in us, and we can no more uſe Them for our Eſtabliſhment, than we are able to make out theſe conditions: &amp; theſe conditions are of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170983:82"/> two ſorts; <hi>viz.</hi> either ſuch as are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in order to our being made Partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in theſe Promiſes, or ſuch as are requiſite in order to our coming to the compleat fruition of the good laid up in them. Reſpecting the former, there is ſo much Counterfeit in the world, and it is a thing ſo eaſy to be miſtaken about: and led into a vain preſumption, yet he troubles them with doubts whether they are indeed true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, or have ſincerely Repented and Turned to God. Now for the clearing up of this, they are to confer the <hi>Rules</hi> given in the Scriptures, and wait for the <hi>Co-Witneſs of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to the latter, the trouble is, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever finds Satan filling him with fears whether he ſhall ever be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them: his faith is ſo <hi>weak,</hi> and the Temptations which Aſſault him are ſo <hi>ſtrong,</hi> that he ſhall fail, and his faith give in: his Obedience is ſo poor and une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that it will never find acceptance with God: and this Perſeverance is a Terrible thing; how ſhall he ever be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hold out againſt all the Furious Shocks which he is to encounter, and be faithful to the Death, and if he do
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170983:83"/> not, be muſt expect to loſe the Crown: It is an hard thing to maintain his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, in the midſt of all the Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and affrightments that are in his way, and if he fail or fall ſhort he is loſt after all: Now if you find your ſelves to be at any time thus ſhaken, your buſineſs is, preſently to repair to the <hi>Everlaſting Covenant,</hi> and there you ſhall find ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and good ſecurity againſt theſe fears. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1 You ſhall here find all theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are thus required of you in the Covenant of Grace to be firmly and faithfully undertaken for by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. For, we obſerved before, that in the Covenant of Redemption, one <hi>Condition</hi> that was laid upon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the Son of God, was that he ſhould <hi>bring many Sons to Glory;</hi> and for that end he undertook to do all that for them and in them, that was requiſite for the accompliſhment of it: ſo that he ſtands obliged not only to anſwer the <hi>Law</hi> for them, but the <hi>Goſpel</hi> too. The fulfilment of every condition that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in order to their Participation in Life Eternal, is incumbent on him to ſee to; If there be any thing, which is a <hi>neceſſary medium</hi> to Glory, required of us,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170983:83"/> he is engaged to ſee it done in us and for us, elſe it would not be a Compleat work of Redemption. If He ſhould deliver us from the <hi>Law,</hi> ſo far as to make it a poſſibility for us to be ſaved by Grace, and yet leave us to Periſh for want of the <hi>Evangelical Obed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> without which there is no Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we were in a miſerable ſtate; for we can no more do this of our ſelves than we could the other: but it is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. That would be an <hi>Arminian mock Redemption;</hi> and it would be but to ſave us from one <hi>Hell,</hi> to throw us into a <hi>Worſe.</hi> But, as the Son of God was to anſwer the <hi>Law</hi> for us, ſo was he to give us the Grace and Strength to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in all the Demands of it: and therefore the ſecurity is in him, whoſe Strength will Manifeſt and Magnify it ſelf in our Weakneſs</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hence you ſhall here find all thoſe <hi>Abſolute Promiſes</hi> which are upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Record, given for your comfort. It is true an Unbeliever can make no challenge of them to himſelf, or make a living of them: they are not a <hi>Diſh</hi> that is ſet before every one to <hi>feed</hi> upon: but a believer may and ought to reckon
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170983:84"/> them to be his own, and to ſuck all the <hi>Marrow and Fatneſs</hi> out of them. And when you have well pondered of theſe Promiſes you may ſtrengthen your Faith by arguing after this manner; <hi>viz.</hi> That although in the Covenant of Grace all theſe things are required of you, and they muſt be found in you if ever you be ſaved; yet in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Redemption all this is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken for: for this is the proper lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of theſe Promiſes. When God ſaith <hi>He will give you a New Heart, and put his Spirit upon you, and put his Fear into your Hearts, and you ſhall never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him, and the like;</hi> theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes belong to ſome, there are they who are deſigned &amp; pointed at by them, and who are they but ſuch as are <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to Salvation from Eternity?</hi> and theſe are they who are <hi>Effectually called in Time.</hi> You may therefore upon the conſideration of your <hi>vocation</hi> be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Accompliſhment of them in you; for though you might fail, yet God cannot.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence alſo Jeſus Chriſt hath Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to ſend his Spirit into the hearts of his people, to dwell in them, to teach
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170983:84"/> them, to keep <hi>them by his Power, and that through Faith to Salvation.</hi> When Jeſus Chriſt left this earth as to his bodily preſence, he then gave his Spirit to be the Guardian of his People, that they might not be left Orphans: and it is he who hath undertaken to do all that in them and for them which they need: to keep their weak Grace alive; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent its being quenched by the many waters of Temptation that would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſwallow it up, and utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it in them: and this is a Fruit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Covenant of Redemption. And hence it comes to paſs, that though Adam in his integrity, loſt all his ſtock by the prevelancy of a Temptation, that was too hard for him, yet a believer in the hand of the Spirit of God, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the frailties that attend upon him, ſhall never loſe his little ſtock, but both keep and encreaſe it. So that if, when we look upon the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> required in the One Covenant, we lay by it, the conſideration of the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking and Proviſion</hi> that is made for the performance of it in another Covenant, that may quiet and ſatisfy our ſouls in this regard, and enable us to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170983:85"/> Triumph over all Doubts and Fears, which Aſſaults us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be therefore directed whither to go for all the ſtrength and aſſiſtance, for the diſcharge of the Duty, which is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you, and required of you in your place and ſtation; and for comfort in the doing of it. We are often diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the weight of Duty, and are ready to ſink under it, upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience we have of our own imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; whereas if we look back unto this Covenant we ſhall there find that taken care for effectually; for here we may obſerve.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Perfect Obedience which was required, and was to Merit our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God, was laid upon Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and hereupon it is taken off from us.</p>
               <p>He was to do as well as to Dy. We have taken notice that his <hi>Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> was required in, and became a Condition of this Covenant, as well as his Paſſive; and God hath reſpect to it: he looks upon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and imputes it to us: and ſo the Law is anſwered, and all the happineſs which man once forfeited
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170983:85"/> is purchaſed. What though we cannot perfectly obey? yet becauſe he hath done it for us, there is our Security, and we may account it ours, becauſe it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in our Name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That <hi>Sincerity,</hi> under our greateſt <hi>imperfections</hi> render our performances <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable</hi> to God. If our <hi>hearts be right</hi> in the Duties we do, if they are True and Faithful to God, if we can truely plead <hi>Uprightneſs and Integrity;</hi> they ſhall <hi>preſerve us.</hi> No weakneſs that inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth our Obedience, ſhall cut it off from his favour, or prevent his <hi>ſmelling a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of reſt in it.</hi> He that had not a <hi>Lamb</hi> to offer, might offer <hi>Two Turtle Doves.</hi> The ground of this is here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt is accepted for us in the Covenant of Redemption, and ſo we come to be accepted through him in the Covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That Chriſt is engaged not only to do <hi>for us,</hi> but <hi>in us,</hi> too, all the works that are needful. All that is requiſite to our pleaſing of God, and obtaining of Glory. His Almighty power ſtands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it: hence <hi>Pauls Prayer</hi> for his <hi>Coloſſians, Col.</hi> 1. 9, 10, 11. In a word,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170983:86"/> This Covenant hath provided a Chriſt for us to go to for all that we can ſtand in need of, in order to the bringing of us home to the Kingdom: <hi>For the Subduing of all our Enemies the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of our Corruptions, the Recovering of us from our Apoſtaſies, the Eſtabliſhing of our Grace, the Perpetuating of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance;</hi> So that there can nothing be wanting for the ſatisfaction of a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul, but here it is to be had ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and the encouragement to go to him with boldneſs for it, is fetched from the conſideration of this Covenant; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe GOD the FATHER ſtands firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Engaged to His SON, for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all this for us; and he cannot deny us when we come and humbly and believingly claim it at his hands, upon this ſcope.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Labour we to <hi>ſee, admire and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify</hi> thoſe riches of Grace that are laid up for poor man in this Covenant. The Covenant of Redemption hath matter enough in it for us to ſtudy upon and contemplate for ever. A believer, when himſelf, cannot look upon this Covenant without admiration, and Extaſy: it is full of unſearchable wonders. Here are the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170983:86"/> greateſt engagements imaginable to oblige us to love and ſerve God. Here is matter enough to Elevate our Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the higheſt ſtrain! for,</p>
               <p n="1">1 Here we learn what were the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting thoughts of God concerning us, even <hi>thoughts of mercy and peace,</hi> when we find our names written in That Book, we are ſure that God Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membered us before we were or any other creature to make mention of us to him: and what a ſweet and raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contemplation is here. <hi>The Phyſician was provided before the Malady was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted,</hi> when we were not, God thought of us for good, and made the way of this good ſure and unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable: he enrolled a Covenant for us in the Records of Eternity. The Father and Son did, of their own accord, thus conſult for the Everlaſting welfare of a company of worthleſs Worms: they contrived the matter between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, reſolved to build the Declarative Glory of Divine Grace upon ſo mean a Subject as ſorry man. Here we ſee what a difference was put between us and the <hi>Children of Wrath; how precious Gods thoughts of us were,</hi> that among ſuch multitudes whom he paſſed by, he
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170983:87"/> ſhould fix his heart upon us, and mark us out for a Kingdom, and how aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſhing a thing is this?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here alſo we may obſerve the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Wiſe Contrivance of mans Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. There are all the Myſteries of Wiſdom concerned in this Covenant. Here is a way found out to Save Fallen Man, which would altogether have puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and non-pluſt the Underſtandings of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>men;</hi> if they had ſat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtudy about it, it would never have come into their thoughts. Nay, the <hi>Angels</hi> themſelves are ſtill amazed at it, and deſirous to be <hi>Gazing</hi> into the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of it, although it be Revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Who could ever have told God, had he ſeen meet to enquire of him, how a Sinner ſhould be Saved, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice remain Inviolated. Now in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, we ſee that all things are ſo contrived as that there is no flaw, nor any the leaſt diſagreement between the Covenant of Works, and the Covenant of Grace, but both have their honour and glory, and yet the ſinner is ſaved out of the hands of the Law, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from Wrath and Vengeance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 26.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170983:87"/> 3. Here we ſee how ſure a ground and foundation there is laid for the certain Salvation of all Gods Elect; in that every thing which was requiſite to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in all the parts of it, is here fully provided: and all that might poſſibly have hindred it, is taken care about that it be removed out of the way. The <hi>Guilt</hi> of Sin lay as a great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſeparate between God and us; and as long as it there lay, there was no coming at him: he was a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Fire; but now this Guilt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved away, and this Mountain is thrown into the depths of the Sea. The pollution of ſin lay as a woful obſtruction to mans happineſs, and whilſt it abode, he muſt needs be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable: but here is a waſhing and a cleanſing prepared, a Fountain opened for it, which can take it all away. There was a Legal Obedience required as the Condition of mans happineſs, and without ſuch a Righteouſneſs, he could not be entituled to it: but here is an Everlaſting Righteouſneſs brought in, and whatſoever elſe might be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, here it is to be found: ſo that there is now nothing to hinder the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170983:88"/> Salvation of every Believer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Here we may read the Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God to his own Word and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to his Son; when we find our ſelves Converted, and made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in ſaving Grace; and ſo we may be led up to the true reaſon of our accepting of Chriſt, by faith in him, not to be in us, or any natural good diſpoſitions of ours, but in the fidelity of God. If he ſhould have let us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to our ſelves, and not have ſought us up and brought us home to Chriſt, as we ſhould never have come to him, ſo we could never have accuſed him of falſhood; for we did not know our ſelves to be the Subjects of thoſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, till by the effect he made it known to us. But becauſe he had promiſed it, therefore he fulfilled it: and this is the reaſon why the <hi>Goſpel</hi> which became a <hi>ſavour of Death</hi> to others, was made a <hi>ſavour of Life</hi> to us: the ſame means that <hi>hardened</hi> others in their ſins, <hi>ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> us, and brake us off from our ſins, and brought us home to God; and this will help to confirm us in the aſſurance that the ſame <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> will do the reſt that remains to be done for us, in
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170983:88"/> the accompliſhment of our compleat Salvation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Here alſo we may acquaint our ſelves with what deep engagements Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt hath laid upon us to love, and fear, and ſerve him, in that he undertook for our Redemption and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from Eternity; and that which ſerves more eſpecially to ſet forth our Obligation and Debt to him in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, is the conſideration how he was circumſtanced in this Covenant, in thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or four reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That it was a free and voluntary engagement on his part. He was under no tie of natural neceſſity to do this work. He was a perſon at full and free liberty in himſelf to be engaged or not engaged for us. It was at his own pleaſure whether he would become a <hi>Surety,</hi> and give himſelf up for our Redemption: Hence that <hi>Joh.</hi> 10 18. <hi>I have Power, &amp;c.</hi> the word implies a <hi>Liberty or a Right to a Thing.</hi> He was a Divine Perſon, and therefore enjoyned in himſelf the higheſt Liberty and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over his own actions. If he had refuſed to do this for us, he had
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170983:89"/> not injured us at all. And needs muſt it be a very great bond which is laid upon us, by one that doth us the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt kindneſs, who was no farther obli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged to it, than he himſelf pleaſed to make himſelf to be: for the more free the love is, the greater doth it appear to be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he thus engaged for us before we deſired it of him. He did not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be asked by us; he did not wait for our peti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions to be put up to him requeſting him that he would put in for us, and become our <hi>Propitiation:</hi> but before we had a being, or were in any capacity of enquiring after him, he then put in, undertook, and made himſelf faſt by a Convenant and a Promiſe. It had been incomparable love for him to have undertaken ſuch a thing for us, upon our moſt ardent and importunate entreaties: yea it would have looked like a thing that was unreaſonable, for us ever to have requeſted him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage himſelf in our behalf: but for him to interpoſe, and take up our cauſe, and become reſponſible for us, <hi>Unſought!</hi> this carries the greateſt Force in it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 9.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170983:89"/> 3 That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> took upon him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt condeſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> been,; <hi>viz</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſinners room <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> provoked the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Wrath</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Law wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> our ſins <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>maki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> like unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> things an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tention, 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>men,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>emies Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ittle kindne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:170983:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
